<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A morall poem, intituled the Legend of Cupid and Psyche. Or Cupid and his mistris As it was lately presented to the Prince Elector. Written by Shackerley Marmion, Gent.</title>
            <title>Legend of Cupid and Psiche</title>
            <author>Marmion, Shackerley, 1603-1639.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1638</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 143 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 50 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A68450</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17444A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S112188</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99847446</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99847446</idno>
            <idno type="VID">12481</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A68450)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12481)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1073:10, 1210:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A morall poem, intituled the Legend of Cupid and Psyche. Or Cupid and his mistris As it was lately presented to the Prince Elector. Written by Shackerley Marmion, Gent.</title>
                  <title>Legend of Cupid and Psiche</title>
                  <author>Marmion, Shackerley, 1603-1639.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[90] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by N. and I. Okes, and are to be sold by H. Sheppard, at his shop in Chancery lane neere Serjants Inne, at the Bible,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1637 [i.e. 1638]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>The "c" in "Psyche" on the title page may be a broken "e".</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-L⁴ M²  (-M2).</note>
                  <note>With an additional engraved title page: Cupid and Psiche. or an epick poem of Cupid, and his mistress .. London. Printed by Iohn Okes, for H: Sheppard. 1638·.</note>
                  <note>The preliminary leaf containing verses to the author comes in two states, signed "A3" or "A4"; one of them is a probably cancel. Quire I also comes in two states, one signed normally, the other with I1,3 signed K1,3.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: Cupid and Psyche.</note>
                  <note>A reissue of the 1637 edition, with engraved title-page date altered.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 17444 on UMI microfilm reel 1073.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the originals in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery and the British Library.</note>
                  <note>Appears at reel 1073 (Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery copy) and at reel 1210 (British Library copy).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:12481:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12481:1"/>
            <p>A Morall Poem, Intituled the Legend of CVPID and Pſyche. Or
CVPID and his <hi>MISTRIS.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As it was lately preſented to the <hi>Prince Elector.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Written</hi> by <hi>Shackerley Marmion, Gent.</hi>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Lucrece</hi> my booke, 'fore <hi>Brutus</hi> did
refraine,</l>
               <l>But <hi>Brutus</hi> gone, <hi>ſhe</hi> tooke it up againe.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>LONDON; Printed by <hi>N.</hi> and <hi>I. Okes,</hi> and are to be
ſold by <hi>H. Sheppard,</hi> at his ſhop in <hi>Chancery lane</hi> neere
<hi>Serjants Inne,</hi> at the Bible. 1637.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:12481:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12481:2"/>
            <head>TO THE HIGH AND MIGHTY, CHARLES LODWICK, Prince Elector, Count
Palatine of the <hi>Rheine,</hi> Arch Dapifer, Vicar of the Sacred Empire, Duke
of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> and Knight of the moſt <hi>Noble order of the
Garter.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>High and Mighty Prince:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is not the greatneſſe of an Oblation, but the ſincerity
which the gods are delighted with: from this hope, and out of an ambitious
zeale, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come your adorers, the <hi>Muſes</hi> amidſt ſo many, and
rich preſents, have prepared this ſlender offering, and are themſelves
both the Prieſts, and the Sacrifice: Their devotion is cloath'd with purity,
and their affections, are both earneſt and powerful; for their wiſhes of
your <pb facs="tcp:12481:3"/>happineſſe are no leſſe than aſſurance, and their
deſires propheſies: For this <hi>Poem,</hi> it was yours e're conceived;
and the hope of being ſo, was both the efficient &amp; finall cauſe of its
pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction; for the Dedication was elder than the birth of it: And however in
the outward barke and title thereof, it appeare painted with vanity, yet is
that, but as a light gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to cover more deepe and weighty my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries.</p>
            <p>The dignity of the Subiect thus calculated, the ſeaſon of the
yeare partly warrants an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptation, but chiefly thoſe royall and freſh
ſpringing ornaments of Candor and ignenui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, which are ſo conſpicuous
through your greatneſſe: It has ever beene the priviledge of
<hi>Poeſie;</hi> to claime acceſſe to the beſt and, moſt noble
perſons; and if this worke ſhall be ſo happy, as to beare the
impreſſe of your Princely approbation, it ſhall then paſſe cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant
to the World, and publiſh the great ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour done to</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Highneſſe moſt humbly devoted: SHACKERLEY
MARMION.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:12481:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To his worthy friend Maſter <hi>Shackerley Marmion,</hi> upon
his <hi>Poem</hi> of <hi>Cupid</hi> and <hi>Pſyche.</hi>
            </head>
            <l>TO give the world aſsurance, in this cold</l>
            <l>And leaden age, that Love muſt ne're be old,</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Cupid</hi> and <hi>Pſyche</hi> thou haſt renderd more</l>
            <l>Youthfull and faire, than did the age of gold:</l>
            <l>And if the ſweetneſſe they had heretofore</l>
            <l>Found leaſt decay, thou doſt it now reſtore</l>
            <l>With large encreaſe, in ſtructing <hi>Love</hi> to love,</l>
            <l>And in his Miſtreſſe more affection move,</l>
            <l>In this thy <hi>Poem;</hi> which thou hadſt a pen</l>
            <l>From <hi>Loves</hi> owne wing to write, powerfull above</l>
            <l>His ſhafts: For thou ſame Iron hearts of men</l>
            <l>Haſt made in Love with <hi>Poeſie;</hi> that till then</l>
            <l>Could not diſcerne her beauty, and leſſe ſee</l>
            <l>Her exc'lence, as it is drawne out by thee,</l>
            <l>In perfect <hi>Love-lines:</hi> Cupid ſmiles to ſee't,</l>
            <l>And crownes his Miſtreſſe with thy Poetry,</l>
            <l>Compos'd of ſyllables, that kiſſe more ſweete</l>
            <l>Then Violets and Roſes when they meeet:</l>
            <l>And we, thine Arts juſt Lovers, as we looke</l>
            <l>On <hi>Cupid</hi> kiſsing <hi>Pſyche,</hi> kiſse thy
Booke.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>Rich. Brome.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:12481:4"/>
            <head>To his loving friend, M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> 
               <hi>Shackerley Marmion,</hi> the
Author.</head>
            <l>FRiend, I have read thy <hi>Poem,</hi> full of wit,</l>
            <l>A Maſter-piece, Ile ſet my ſeale to it:</l>
            <l>Let Judges reade, and ignorance be gone:</l>
            <l>'Tis not for vulgar thumbs to ſweat upon</l>
            <l>This learned worke: thy Muſe flies in her place:</l>
            <l>And Eagle-like, lookes <hi>Phaebus</hi> in the face.</l>
            <l>Let thoſe voluminous Authours, that affect</l>
            <l>Fame rather great, than good, thy worth reject.</l>
            <l>Jewels are ſmall: how'nlike art thou to thoſe,</l>
            <l>That tire out Rime, and Verſe, till they trot Proſe?</l>
            <l>And ride the Muſes <hi>Pegaſus,</hi> poore jade,</l>
            <l>Till he be found red; and make that their trade:</l>
            <l>And to fill up the ſufferings of the beaſt,</l>
            <l>Foot in themſelves three hundred miles at leaſt.</l>
            <l>Theſe have no mercy on the Paper rheames,</l>
            <l>But produce plaies, as ſchole boys do write theams.</l>
            <l>Thou keepſt thy Muſe in breath, and if men wage</l>
            <l>Gold on her head, will better runne the ſtage:</l>
            <l>And 'tis more praiſe, than hadſt thou labout'd in't,</l>
            <l>To brand the world with twenty ſuch in print.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>Francis Tuckyr.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:12481:4"/>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <head>To his worthy friend Maſter <hi>Shackerley Marmion,</hi> upon
his <hi>Poem</hi> of <hi>Cupid</hi> and <hi>Pſyche.</hi>
            </head>
            <l>TO give the world aſsurance, in this cold</l>
            <l>And leaden age, that Love muſt ne're be old,</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Cupid</hi> and <hi>Pſyche</hi> thou haſt renderd more</l>
            <l>Youthfull and faire, than did the age of gold:</l>
            <l>And if the ſweetneſſe they had heretofore</l>
            <l>Found leaſt decay, thou doſt it now reſtore</l>
            <l>With large encreaſe, in ſtructing <hi>Love</hi> to love,</l>
            <l>And in his Miſtreſſe more affection move,</l>
            <l>In this thy <hi>Poem;</hi> which thou hadſt a pen</l>
            <l>From <hi>Loves</hi> owne wing to write, powerfull above</l>
            <l>His ſhafts: For thou ſame Iron hearts of men</l>
            <l>Haſt made in Love with <hi>Poeſie;</hi> that till then</l>
            <l>Could not diſcerne her beauty, and leſſe ſee</l>
            <l>Her exc'lence, as it is drawne out by thee,</l>
            <l>In perfect <hi>Love-lines:</hi> Cupid ſmiles to ſee't,</l>
            <l>And crownes his Miſtreſſe with thy Poetry,</l>
            <l>Compos'd of ſyllables, that kiſſe more ſweete</l>
            <l>Then Violets and Roſes when they meeet:</l>
            <l>And we, thine Arts juſt Lovers, as we looke</l>
            <l>On <hi>Cupid</hi> kiſsing <hi>Pſyche,</hi> kiſse thy
Booke.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>Rich. Brome.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:12481:5"/>
            <head>To his loving friend, M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> 
               <hi>Shackerley Marmion,</hi> the
Author.</head>
            <l>FRiend, I have read thy <hi>Poem,</hi> full of wit,</l>
            <l>A Maſter-piece, Ile ſet my ſeale to it:</l>
            <l>Let Judges reade, and ignorance be gone:</l>
            <l>'Tis not for vulgar thumbs to ſweat upon</l>
            <l>This learned worke: thy Muſe flies in her place:</l>
            <l>And Eagle-like, lookes <hi>Phaebus</hi> in the face.</l>
            <l>Let thoſe voluminous Authours, that affect</l>
            <l>Fame rather great, than good, thy worth reject.</l>
            <l>Jewels are ſmall: how'nlike art thou to thoſe,</l>
            <l>That tire out Rime, and Verſe, till they trot Proſe?</l>
            <l>And ride the Muſes <hi>Pegaſus,</hi> poore jade,</l>
            <l>Till he be found red; and make that their trade:</l>
            <l>And to fill up the ſufferings of the beaſt,</l>
            <l>Foot in themſelves three hundred miles at leaſt.</l>
            <l>Theſe have no mercy on the Paper rheames,</l>
            <l>But produce plaies, as ſchole boys do write theams.</l>
            <l>Thou keepſt thy Muſe in breath, and if men wage</l>
            <l>Gold on her head, will better runne the ſtage:</l>
            <l>And 'tis more praiſe, than hadſt thou labout'd in't,</l>
            <l>To brand the world with twenty ſuch in print.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>Francis Tuckyr.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:12481:5"/>
            <head>To his true friend the Author, Maiſter <hi>Shackerley
Marmion, &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hat need I racke the limbs of my weake <hi>Muſe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To fill a page might ſerve for better uſe?</l>
               <l>Then make ſome ſquint-ey'd Reader cenſure me</l>
               <l>A Flatterer, for iuſtly prayſing <hi>thee?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>It is enough, (and in that cauſes right</l>
               <l>Many thy former <hi>workes</hi> may boldly fight)</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>He for a good one muſt this <hi>piece</hi> allow,</l>
               <l>Reades but the <hi>Title,</hi> and thy <hi>Name</hi> below.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Tho. Nabbes.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <head>Of my worthy friend, Mr. <hi>Shackerley Marmion,</hi> upon his
Poem, of <hi>Cupid</hi> and <hi>Pſyche.</hi>
            </head>
            <l>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Ove</hi> and the <hi>Soule</hi> are two things, both
<hi>Divine,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Thy task (friend <hi>Marmion</hi>) now, which once was mine.</l>
            <l>What I writ was Dramatical; thy <hi>Muſe</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Runnes in an Epick ſtraine, which they ſtill uſe,</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:12481:6"/>
            <l>Who write Heroicke Poems. Thine is ſuch,</l>
            <l>Which when I read, I could not praiſe too much.</l>
            <l>The <hi>Argument</hi> is high, and not within</l>
            <l>Their ſhallow reach to catch, who hold no ſin</l>
            <l>To taxe, what they conceive not; the beſt minds</l>
            <l>Iudge trees by fruit, not by their leaves and rinds.</l>
            <l>And ſuch can find (full knowledge having gain'd)</l>
            <l>Jn leaden Fables, golden truths contain'd.</l>
            <l>Thy ſubjects of that nature, a ſublime</l>
            <l>And weighty rapture, which being cloath'd in ryme,</l>
            <l>Carries ſuch ſweetneſſe with't, as hadſt thou ſung</l>
            <l>Vnto <hi>Apollo's</hi> Harpe, being newly ſtrung.</l>
            <l>Theſe, had they iſſued from an others Pen,</l>
            <l>A ſtranger, and unknowne to me, I then</l>
            <l>Could not have bin ſo pleaſ'd: But from a Friend,</l>
            <l>Where I might enuy, I muſt now commend.</l>
            <l>And glad J am this faire courſe thou haſt runne,</l>
            <l>Vnvext to ſee my ſelfe ſo farre out done.</l>
            <l>Twixt Jntimates, who mutuall love profeſſe,</l>
            <l>More's not requir'd, and mine could ſhow no leſse.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thomas Heywood.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="argument">
            <pb facs="tcp:12481:6"/>
            <head>The Argument.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here were inhabitant in a certaine Cittie, a King and Queene,
who had three Daughters; the elder two of a moderate, and meane beauty; but the
yon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt was of ſo curious, ſo pleaſing a feature, and exact ſymmetry
of body, that men e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem'd her generally a Goddeſſe, and the
<hi>Venus</hi> of the earth. Her ſiſters being happily married to their
deſires and dignities, ſhee only out of a ſuper-excellency of perfection,
became rather the ſubject of adoration, then <hi>Love. Venus</hi> conceiving
an offence, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious of her good parts, incites <hi>Cupid</hi> to a
revenge, and ſevere vindication of his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers honour. <hi>Cupid</hi> like a
fine Archer, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to execute his mothers deſigne, fals in love with the
<hi>maide,</hi> and wounds himſelfe. <hi>Apollo,</hi> by <hi>Cupids</hi>
ſubornation, adjudges her in <pb facs="tcp:12481:7"/>marriage to a <hi>Serpent.</hi> Vpon
which, like <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dromeda,</hi> ſhe is left chain'd to a Rocke, her marriage
being celebrated, rather with fune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall obſequies, than Hymenaeall
ſolemnities. In this miſerable affright ſhe is borne farre a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way by the
weſt Wind, to a goodly faire houſe, whoſe wealth and ſtatelineſſe
no praiſe can determine. Her husband in the deadneſſe, and ſolitude of
night, did oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times enioy her, and as he entred in obſcuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, ſo he
departed in ſilence, without once making himſelfe knowne unto her: thus
ſhe continued for a long ſeaſon, being onely waited upon by the
miniſtery of the winds, and voyces; Her ſiſters came every day to feeke,
and bewaile her; and though her hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band did with many threats prohibit her the
ſight of them; yet naturall affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on prevailed above coniugall duty; for
ſhe never ceaſed with teares to ſolicite him, till he had permitted their
acceſſe. They no no ſooner arived, but inſtantly corrupt her, and with
wicked counſell deprave her un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, infuſing a beliefe, that
ſhe had <pb facs="tcp:12481:7"/>married, and did nightly embrace a true Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent; nor are
they yet contented to turne the heaven of her ſecurity into the hell of
ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion, but with many importunities proceed, exhorting her to kill him,
which ſhe alſo aſſents unto: Thus credulity proves the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of
deceite, and curioſity the Step-mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of ſafety: Having thus prepar'd for
his deſtruction, the Sceane is altered, and ſhee acts the Tragedy of her
owne happy for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes; for comming with an intent to miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe him, ſo
ſoone as the light had diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered what he was, ſhee fals into an
extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity of love and paſsion, being altogether raviſht with his beauty
and habiliments; and while ſhe kiſſes him, with as little mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty as
care; the burning Lampe drops upon his ſhoulder, whereupon her husband
furi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly awakes, and having with many expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtulations abandoned her
falſehood, ſcornes and forſakes her: the maide after a tedious pilgrimage
to regaine his love and ſociety: <hi>Ceres</hi> and <hi>Juno</hi> having both
repulſed her, freely at the laſt offers up her ſelfe to <hi>Venus,</hi> 
               <pb facs="tcp:12481:8"/>where through her iniunctions and impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious commands: ſhe is
courſely intreated, and ſet to many hard and grievous taskes: as firſt
the ſeperation of ſeverall graines; with the fetching of the
<hi>Stygian</hi> water, and the golden fleece, and the boxe of beauty from
<hi>Proſerpine;</hi> all which by divine aſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance being performed,
ſhee is reconcil'd, and in the preſence of all the gods mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried to her
husband: the wedding is ſolem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niz'd in heaven.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="apology">
            <pb facs="tcp:12481:8"/>
            <head>The Mitheology.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Y the City is meant the World: by the King and Queene, God, and
Nature: by the two elder ſiſters, the fleſh and the will: by the laſt
the ſoule, which is the moſt beautifull, and the youngeſt, ſince ſhe
is infu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, after the body is faſhioned: <hi>Venus,</hi> by which is
underſtood luſt is feigned to envy her, and ſtirre up <hi>Cupid,</hi>
which is Deſire, to deſtroy her: But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Deſire has equall
relation both to good and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill, he is here brought in to love the ſoule,
and to be ioynd with her, whom alſo he perſwades not to ſee his face;
that is, not to learne his delights and vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties: for <hi>Adam,</hi> though he
were naked, yet he ſaw it not, till he had eaten of the tree of
concupiſcence. And whereas, ſhe is ſaid to burne him, with the
deſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of the Lampe; by that is underſtood, that ſhe vomits out the
flames of deſire, which was hid in her breaſt; for deſire the more it is
kindled, the more it burnes, and makes as it were a bliſter in the minde.
thus, like <hi>Eve,</hi> being made naked through deſire, ſhe is 
<pb facs="tcp:12481:9"/>caſt out of all happineſſe, exhil'd from her houſe, and
toſt with many dangers: By <hi>Ceres</hi> and <hi>Iuno</hi> both repulſing
of her, is meant, that neither wealth, nor ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, can ſuccour a
diſtreſſed ſoule: in the ſeparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſeverall graines, is
underſtood the act of the ſoule, which is recollection; and the
ſubſtance of, that act, her fore-paſt ſinnes: by her going to hell and
thoſe ſeverall occurrences, are meant the many degrees of deſpaire: by
the <hi>Stygian</hi> water, the teares of repentance; and by the golden fleece,
her forgiveneſse. All which, as in the argument is ſpecified, being by
divine providence accompliſht, ſhe is married to her ſpouſe in
heaven.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:12481:9"/>
            <head>A Morall Poem, <hi>Intituled the Legend of</hi> CUPID
<hi>and</hi> PSICHE.</head>
            <div n="1" type="book">
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>THE FIRST SECTION.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Ruth ſayes of old, and we muſt owe that truth</l>
                     <l>Vnto tradition, when the world in youth,</l>
                     <l>W<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> was the glode<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                        <hi>age,</hi> brought for the
<hi>pen,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Love</hi> and the <hi>Muſes,</hi> which fince gave to
men</l>
                     <l>Inheritance of Fame, for theſe began</l>
                     <l>At once, and were all coetanean.</l>
                     <l>A happy ſeaſon, when the ayre was cleare;</l>
                     <l>No ſickneſſe, nor infection did appeare,</l>
                     <l>No ſullen change of ſeaſons did moleſt</l>
                     <l>The fruitfull ſoyle, but the whole yeare was bleſt</l>
                     <l>With a perpetuall <hi>Spring,</hi> no <hi>Winter</hi>
ſtorme</l>
                     <l>Did criſpe the <hi>Hills,</hi> nor mildew blaſt the
<hi>Corne:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Yet happier farre, in that it forth did bring</l>
                     <l>The ſubject of this verſe, whereof I ſing</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12481:10"/>
                     <l>Vnder the <hi>Zenith</hi> of Heavens milke-white way,</l>
                     <l>Is a faire country called <hi>Luſinia,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>'Tis Natures chiefeſt Wardrop, where doe lye</l>
                     <l>Her ornaments of rich veriety:</l>
                     <l>Where firſt her glorious Mantle ſhe puts on,</l>
                     <l>When through the world ſhe rides proceſſion;</l>
                     <l>Here dwelt a King and Queene of mighty power,</l>
                     <l>Iudg'd for their vertues, worthy ſuch a dower.</l>
                     <l>They had betwixt themſelves three Daughters born,</l>
                     <l>Conſpicuous for their comlineſſe and forme.</l>
                     <l>The elder two did neither much excell,</l>
                     <l>But then the younger had no paralell;</l>
                     <l>Whoſe lovely cheekes with Heavenly luſter ſhone,</l>
                     <l>And eyes were farre too bright to looke upon:</l>
                     <l>Nay, it is credible, though fancies wing</l>
                     <l>Should mount above the <hi>Orbes,</hi> and thence downe
bring</l>
                     <l>Th' Elixar of all beauty, and diſpence</l>
                     <l>Vnto one creature, the whole influence,</l>
                     <l>And harmony of the Speares, it might not dare</l>
                     <l>VVith her for face and feature, to compare</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Zeuxis</hi> the painter, who to draw one peece,</l>
                     <l>Survay'd the choyceſt Virgins of all <hi>Greece,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Had reſted here, his Art without this ſtir,</l>
                     <l>Might have beene bounded, and confin'd in her.</l>
                     <l>Looke how the ſpiced fields in <hi>Autumne</hi>
ſmell,</l>
                     <l>And rich perfumes, that in <hi>Arabia</hi> dwell:</l>
                     <l>Such was her fragrant ſweetneſſe, the Sunnes Bird,</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Phaenix</hi> fled farre off, and was afeard</l>
                     <l>To be ſeene neere, leaſt ſhe his pride ſhould
quell,</l>
                     <l>Or make him ſeeme a common ſpectacle.</l>
                     <l>Nor did the painted Peacocke once preſume,</l>
                     <l>Within her preſence to diſplay his plume.</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12481:10"/>
                     <l>Nor Roſe, nor Lilly durſt their Silkes unfold,</l>
                     <l>But ſhut their leaves up like the Mary gold.</l>
                     <l>They all had beene ill favour'd, ſhe alone</l>
                     <l>Was judg'd the Miſtreſſe of perfection.</l>
                     <l>Her fame ſpread farre abroad, and thither brought</l>
                     <l>Thouſands, that gazing worſhipt her, and thought</l>
                     <l>The God deſſe, whom the greene-fac'd Sea had bred,</l>
                     <l>And dew of foaming waves had nouriſhed.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Venus</hi> her ſelfe, regardieſſe of her
honour,</l>
                     <l>Did live with mortals, whoſoe'r lookt on her,</l>
                     <l>Even moſt prophane, did think ſhe was divine,</l>
                     <l>And grudg'd not to doe worſhip to her ſhrine.</l>
                     <l>For this cauſe, <hi>Venus</hi> Temples were defac'd,</l>
                     <l>Her ſacrifice, and Ceremonies rac'd;</l>
                     <l>Her widdowed Altars in cold aſhes mourn'd,</l>
                     <l>Her Images uncrown'd, her Groves deform'd:</l>
                     <l>Her Rites were all polluted with contempt,</l>
                     <l>For none to <hi>Paphos,</hi> nor <hi>Cytheros</hi> went.</l>
                     <l>This Maide was ſole ador'd, <hi>Venus</hi>
diſpleas'd,</l>
                     <l>Might in this Virgin onely be appeas'd:</l>
                     <l>The people in the ſtreet to her would bow,</l>
                     <l>And as ſhe paſt along, would Garlands ſtrow.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Venus</hi> at this conceiv'd a jealous ire,</l>
                     <l>(For heavenly minds burne with an earthly fire)</l>
                     <l>And ſpake with indignation, what ſhall I,</l>
                     <l>Mother of Elements, and loſtieſt skie,</l>
                     <l>Beginner of the world, Parent of Nature,</l>
                     <l>Pertake mine honour with an earthly creature?</l>
                     <l>Shall ſilly girles deſtin'd to death, and Fate,</l>
                     <l>My high-borne name, and ſtile contaminate?</l>
                     <l>In vaine did then the <hi>Phrygian</hi> Shepheard give</l>
                     <l>The Ball to me, when three of us did ſtrive</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12481:11"/>
                     <l>Who ſhould excel in beauty, and all ſtood</l>
                     <l>Naked before the Boy, to tempt his blood,</l>
                     <l>When they with Roy all gifts ſought to beguile</l>
                     <l>His judgement, I alur'd him with a ſmile:</l>
                     <l>But this uſurper of my dignities,</l>
                     <l>Shall have but little cauſe to boaſt the prize;</l>
                     <l>With that ſhe call'd her raſh, and winged child</l>
                     <l>Arm'd with Bow, Torch, and quiver: that is wild</l>
                     <l>With miſchiefe; he that with his evil waies</l>
                     <l>Corrupts all publick diſcipline, and ſtraies</l>
                     <l>Through chambers in the night, &amp; with falfe beames,</l>
                     <l>Or with his ſtinging Arrowes, or with dreames,</l>
                     <l>Tempts unto luſt, and does no good at all:</l>
                     <l>This childe I ſay did <hi>Venus</hi> to her call,</l>
                     <l>And ſtirres him up with words malitious,</l>
                     <l>That was by nature too licentious:</l>
                     <l>For bringing him where <hi>Pſyche</hi> dwelt, for ſo</l>
                     <l>This Maid was call'd, ſhe there unfolds her woe,</l>
                     <l>And emulous tale. <hi>Cupid</hi> quoth ſhe, my ſtay,</l>
                     <l>My onely ſtrength, &amp; power, whoſe boundles
ſway,</l>
                     <l>Contemnes the thunder of my Father <hi>Iove,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>I here intreate thee by thy Mothers love,</l>
                     <l>Thoſe wounding ſweets, and ſweet wounds of thy
Quiver,</l>
                     <l>And honey burnings of thy torch, deliver</l>
                     <l>My Soule from griefe revenge me on this mayd</l>
                     <l>And all her boaſted beauty ſee decay'd,</l>
                     <l>Or elſe ſtrike her in love with one ſo poore,</l>
                     <l>So miſerably loſt, ſtript of all ſtore</l>
                     <l>Of meanes, or vertue; ſo deform'd of limb,</l>
                     <l>That none in all the world may equall him.</l>
                     <l>To move her Sonne, no flattering words ſhe ſpar'd,</l>
                     <l>But breath'd on him with kiſſes, long and hard,</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12481:11"/>
                     <l>This done; ſhe haſts to the next ebbing ſhore,</l>
                     <l>And with her rofie feet inſulting ore</l>
                     <l>The ſubmiſſe waves, a <hi>Dolphin</hi> ſhe
beſtrides,</l>
                     <l>And on the utmoſt Billows proudly rides.</l>
                     <l>A troupe of <hi>Tritons</hi> were ſtraight ſounding
heard,</l>
                     <l>And rough <hi>Portumnus</hi> with his moſſy beard,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Salacia</hi> heavy with her fiſhy traine,</l>
                     <l>And <hi>Nereus</hi> daughters came to entertaine</l>
                     <l>The Sea-borne Goddeſſe; ſome plaid on a ſhell,</l>
                     <l>Some with their Garments labour'd to expell</l>
                     <l>The ſcorching heat, and Sun-ſhine from her face,</l>
                     <l>And other ſome did hold a looking-glaſſe:</l>
                     <l>All theſe in triumph by the <hi>Dolphin</hi> ſwam,</l>
                     <l>And followed <hi>Venus</hi> to the Ocean;</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Phyche</hi> the while, in this great height of
bliſſe,</l>
                     <l>Yet reapes no fruit of all her happineſſe,</l>
                     <l>For neither King, nor Prince, nor Potentate,</l>
                     <l>Nor any durſt attempt her for a mate,</l>
                     <l>But as a poliſht picture her admire,</l>
                     <l>And in that admiration ceaſe deſire:</l>
                     <l>Her Siſters both, whoſe moderate beauty none</l>
                     <l>Did much deſpiſe, nor much contemplate on,</l>
                     <l>VVere to their wiſhes happily contracted,</l>
                     <l>And by two Kings eſpouſ'd. <hi>Pſyche</hi>
diſtracted</l>
                     <l>Becauſe ſhe had no lover, penſive ſate</l>
                     <l>In mind, and body, and began to hate,</l>
                     <l>And curſe that beauty, and eſteeme at nought,</l>
                     <l>Which, but was excellent, had no other fault.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Cupid</hi> now in a cauſeleſſe rage was gone,</l>
                     <l>To whet his Arrowes on a bloody ſtone,</l>
                     <l>As if he were t'encounter with ſome maine</l>
                     <l>Monſter, like <hi>Python,</hi> by <hi>Apollo</hi>
ſlaine,</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12481:12"/>
                     <l>Or <hi>Iove,</hi> or <hi>Titan</hi> lame, or once agen,</l>
                     <l>Draw the pale Moone downe to the <hi>Latmian</hi> Den,</l>
                     <l>Or with Loves fire great <hi>Pluto</hi> to annoy,</l>
                     <l>For theſe were workes of <hi>labour,</hi> and the Boy</l>
                     <l>Was ignorant, how matters would ſucceed,</l>
                     <l>Or what the fare of Beauty had Decreed.</l>
                     <l>Therefore he fyl'd his arrowes ſharpe and ſmal,</l>
                     <l>To pierce what ever they ſhould meet withal.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And vow'd,</hi> if cauſe were, he his
<hi>ſhafts</hi> would ſhiver,</l>
                     <l>'Gainſt <hi>Pſyches</hi> breaſt, and empty all his
Quiver.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Themis</hi> a Goddeſſe, whom great <hi>Iove</hi> had
ſent</l>
                     <l>Into the World, for good, or puniſhment,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>As juſtice</hi> ſhould require, when ſhe did
heare</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Cupid</hi> ſo proudly boaſt, againe did
ſweare,</l>
                     <l>That <hi>ſhe</hi> his haughty malice would abate,</l>
                     <l>And turne the edge, both of his <hi>ſhafts,</hi> and
<hi>hate.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And having thus diſarm'd him, ten to one,</l>
                     <l>VVould change his <hi>fury</hi> to <hi>affection.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>A</hi> clap of <hi>Thunder</hi> all about them
ſhooke,</l>
                     <l>To ratifie, what <hi>Themis</hi> undertooke.</l>
                     <l>Then both together went, and entring found,</l>
                     <l>Faire <hi>Pſyche,</hi> with her looks fixt on the
ground.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Honor</hi> and <hi>Modeſty,</hi> with equall
grace,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Simplicity</hi> and <hi>truth,</hi> ſmil'd in her
face.</l>
                     <l>But riſing up, there ſhot from eyther eye,</l>
                     <l>Such beames, as did <hi>Loves</hi> ſenſes
ſtupefie.</l>
                     <l>And as in this diſtraction <hi>he</hi> did ſtand,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>He</hi> let his <hi>arrowes</hi> fall out of his
hand.</l>
                     <l>VVhich <hi>Themis</hi> laughing tooke, and thence
conuay'd,</l>
                     <l>VVhi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſt
<hi>Cupid</hi> minded nothing but the <hi>Mayde.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Then did <hi>he</hi> crye amaz'd, what fence is here?</l>
                     <l>Beauty and Vertue have no other ſpheare.</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12481:12"/>
                     <l>Her brow's a Caſtle, and each lip a Fort,</l>
                     <l>Where thouſand armed Deities reſort</l>
                     <l>To guard the golden fruit from all ſurprize,</l>
                     <l>Chaſtly, and ſafe, as the <hi>Heſperides.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Pardon me, <hi>Venus,</hi> if I thee abridge</l>
                     <l>Of this unjuſt revenge; 'twere ſacrilidge,</l>
                     <l>Beyond <hi>Prometheus</hi> theft, to quench ſuch fire,</l>
                     <l>Or ſteale it from <hi>her</hi> eyes, but to inſpire</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Cupids</hi> owne breaſt, in all <hi>Loves</hi>
ſpoyles, I yet</l>
                     <l>Never beheld ſo rich a Cabinet.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Iove,</hi> here for ever, here, my heart confine,</l>
                     <l>And let me all my Empery refigne.</l>
                     <l>Then looking downe, he found himſfelfe bereft</l>
                     <l>Of his looſe armes, and ſmil'd at <hi>Themis</hi>
theft;</l>
                     <l>Becauſe he knew, ſhe might as ſoone abide</l>
                     <l>Fire in her boſome, as <hi>Loves</hi> arrows hide.</l>
                     <l>But that they muſt againe with ſhame be ſent,</l>
                     <l>And claime, for the poſſeſſion, a deare rent:</l>
                     <l>Yet one dropt out by chance, and 'twas the beſt</l>
                     <l>Of all the bundle, and the curiouſeſt.</l>
                     <l>The plumes were colour'd azure, white, and red,</l>
                     <l>The ſhaft painted alike downe to the head,</l>
                     <l>Which was of burniſht Gold: this <hi>Cupid</hi> tooke,</l>
                     <l>And in revenge, through his owne boſome ſtrooke:</l>
                     <l>Then ſighing call'd, You <hi>Lovers</hi> all, in
chiefe)</l>
                     <l>Whom I have wrong'd, come tryumph at my griefe;</l>
                     <l>See, and be ſatisfied for all my ſinne,</l>
                     <l>'Tis not one place that I am pained in,</l>
                     <l>My Arrows venome is diſperſed round,</l>
                     <l>And beauties ſigne is potent in each wound.</l>
                     <l>Thus he with pitty did himſelfe deplore,</l>
                     <l>Foe never pitty enter'd him before.</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12481:13"/>
                     <l>Ill as he was, he tooke his flight, and came</l>
                     <l>Vnto the palace of the Sun, whoſe flame</l>
                     <l>VVas farre inferiour to what <hi>Cupid</hi> felt;</l>
                     <l>And ſaid, deare <hi>Phoebus,</hi> if I ſtill have
dealt</l>
                     <l>Like a true friend, and ſtood thee in ſome ſteed,</l>
                     <l>VVhen thou for love didſt like a ſhepheard feed,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Admetus</hi> Cattle, now thine helpe impart,</l>
                     <l>Tis not for Phiſicke, though I am ſick at heart,</l>
                     <l>That I implore, but through thy skill devine</l>
                     <l>The faireſt <hi>Pſyche</hi> for my wife aſſigne:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Phoebus</hi> aſſents, and did not long delay,</l>
                     <l>To make it good by a Prophetick way;</l>
                     <l>Her Father fearing for the injury,</l>
                     <l>Offerd to <hi>Venus</hi> ſacred Deity,</l>
                     <l>Conſults the <hi>Delpick</hi> Oracle, who thus</l>
                     <l>Expounds his mind in tearmes ambiguous.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>The Oracle.</head>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Your Daughter bring to a ſteepe mountaine
ſpire,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Inveſted with a funerall attire;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Expect no good, but bind her to a ſtake,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>No mortall wight, her for a wife ſhall take:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>But a huge venomn'd Serpent, that does fly</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>With ſpeckled wings, above the ſtarry sky.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And downe againe, does the whole Earth moleſt</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>With ſire, and ſword, and all kind of
unreſt,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>So great in malice, and ſo ſtrong in might,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>That Heaven, and hell doe tremble at his
flight.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The King affrighted what this ſpeech ſhould weene</l>
                     <l>Goes ſlow, and ſadly home unto his Queene,</l>
                     <l>Both ponder in their mind the ſtrange prediction,</l>
                     <l>VVhether it were a riddle, or a fiction:</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12481:13"/>
                     <l>What gloſſe it might endure, and what pretence,</l>
                     <l>Whither a verball, or a miſtick ſence;</l>
                     <l>Which caſt about in vaine, they both bewaile</l>
                     <l>Their Daughters chance, but griefe can not prevaile;</l>
                     <l>But that ſhe muſt fulfill the <hi>Delpicke</hi>
doome,</l>
                     <l>Or worſer plagues are threatned in the roome:</l>
                     <l>And now the pitchy torches lighted are,</l>
                     <l>And for her fatall Marriage they prepare.</l>
                     <l>Songs are to howlings turn'd, bright fire to fume,</l>
                     <l>And pleaſant muſicke to the <hi>Lydian</hi> tune:</l>
                     <l>For <hi>Hymens Saffron</hi> weed, that ſhould adorne</l>
                     <l>Young bluſhing Brides, <hi>Pſyche</hi> is forc'd to
mourne,</l>
                     <l>And for her mourning a blacke mantle weares,</l>
                     <l>With which ſhe gently wipes away her teares.</l>
                     <l>Thus all the City waite her in ſad wiſe,</l>
                     <l>Not to her wedding, but her obſequies;</l>
                     <l>But whilſt her parents weake excuſes make,</l>
                     <l>And vaine delaies, thus <hi>Pſyche</hi> them
beſpake?</l>
                     <l>Why doe you thus with deepe fetch't ſighs perplex</l>
                     <l>Your moſt unhappy age? why doe you vexe</l>
                     <l>Your ſpirit, which is mine, and thus diſgrace</l>
                     <l>With fruitleſſe teares, your venerable face?</l>
                     <l>Why doe you teare your haire, and beat your breſt?</l>
                     <l>Are theſe the hopefull iſſues, and the bleſt</l>
                     <l>Rewards for beauty? then ought you lament,</l>
                     <l>When all the City with a joyn'd conſent</l>
                     <l>Did ſtile me the new <hi>Venus,</hi> and aſcrib'd</l>
                     <l>Thoſe honours which to mortals arc deny'd.</l>
                     <l>'Twas your ambition firſt pluckt on my ſhame,</l>
                     <l>I ſee, and feele my ruine in her name:</l>
                     <l>'Tis now to late, we ſuffer under thoſe</l>
                     <l>Deepe wounds of envy, which the Gods impoſe;</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12481:14"/>
                     <l>Where is the rocke? why doe you linger ſo?</l>
                     <l>Leade hence, my thinks I long to undergoe</l>
                     <l>This happy Marriage, and I long to ſee</l>
                     <l>My noble Husband, whatſoere he bee:</l>
                     <l>Into his armes, ô let me ſoone be hurl'd,</l>
                     <l>That's borne for the deſtruction of the world.</l>
                     <l>This ſaid, each ſtander by, with hang'd downe head</l>
                     <l>And mournfull pompe the Virgin followed,</l>
                     <l>And to the place prefixt her armes they tye,</l>
                     <l>Then howling forth a dolefull Elegy,</l>
                     <l>Depart from her in teares, wiſhing from farre</l>
                     <l>Some winged <hi>Perſeus</hi> might deliver her.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Pſyche</hi> affrighted thus, and they all gone,</l>
                     <l>A gentle gale of wind came poſting on,</l>
                     <l>Who with his whiſpers having charm'd her feares,</l>
                     <l>The maid aſleep on his ſoft boſome beares.</l>
                     <l>This wind is called <hi>Zephirus,</hi> whoſe mild</l>
                     <l>And fruifull breath gets the young ſpring with child,</l>
                     <l>Filling her wombe with ſuch delicious heat,</l>
                     <l>As breeds the blooming Roſe, and Violet:</l>
                     <l>Him <hi>Cupid</hi> for his delicacy choſe,</l>
                     <l>And did this amorous taske on him impoſe,</l>
                     <l>To fetch his Miſtreſſe; but leaſt he ſhould
burne</l>
                     <l>With beauties fire, he bad him ſoone returne;</l>
                     <l>But all in vaine, for promiſes are fraile,</l>
                     <l>And vertue flyes, when love once blowes the ſayle,</l>
                     <l>For as ſhe ſlept, he lingred on his way,</l>
                     <l>And oft embrac'd, and kiſt her as his praye,</l>
                     <l>And gaz'd to ſee how farre me did ſurpaſſe</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Erichthens</hi> Daughter, wife to <hi>Boreas,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Faire <hi>Orythia;</hi> and as ſhe began</l>
                     <l>To waxe hot through his motion, he would fan</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12481:14"/>
                     <l>And coole her with his wings, which did diſperſe</l>
                     <l>A perfum'd ſent, through all the vniverſe;</l>
                     <l>For 'fore that time, no fragrant ſmell did live</l>
                     <l>In any thing, till <hi>Pſyche</hi> did it give:</l>
                     <l>Hearbes, Gummes, and ſpices had perhaps a name,</l>
                     <l>But their firſt odours from her breathing came:</l>
                     <l>And in this manner <hi>Zephirus</hi> flew on</l>
                     <l>With wanton gyres, through every region</l>
                     <l>Of the vaſt ayre, then brought her to a vale,</l>
                     <l>Where thouſand ſeverall flowers her ſweets exhale:</l>
                     <l>The whilſt her parents rob'd of her deare ſight,</l>
                     <l>Devote themſelves to everlaſting night.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>The Second Section.</head>
                  <l>THus <hi>Pſyche</hi> on a graſſy bed did lye,</l>
                  <l>Adorn'd with <hi>Floraes</hi> richeſt tapeſtry,</l>
                  <l>Where all her ſences with ſoft ſlumber bound,</l>
                  <l>At laſt awakt, and riſing from a ſwound</l>
                  <l>She ſpies a wood, with faire trees beautifi'd,</l>
                  <l>And a pure chriſtall Fountaine by the ſide;</l>
                  <l>A Kingly Palace ſtood not farr apart,</l>
                  <l>Built not with humane hands, but devine <hi>Art;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For by the ſtructure men might gueſſe it be</l>
                  <l>The habitation of ſome Deity:</l>
                  <l>The Roofe within was curiouſly o're ſpread</l>
                  <l>With <hi>Ivory,</hi> and Gold enamelled;</l>
                  <l>The Gold was burniſht, gliſtering like a flame,</l>
                  <l>And Golden pillers did ſupport the ſame;</l>
                  <l>The walles were all with Silver wainſcott lin'd,</l>
                  <l>With ſeverall Beaſts, and Pictures there inſhrin'd,</l>
                  <l>The Floure, and Pavement with like glory ſhone,</l>
                  <l>Cut in rare figures, made of pretious Stone,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12481:15"/>
                  <l>That though the Sun ſhould hide his light away,</l>
                  <l>You might behold the houſe through its owne day.</l>
                  <l>Sure 'twas ſome wondrous power by <hi>arts</hi> extent</l>
                  <l>That fancied forth ſo great an argument:</l>
                  <l>And no leſſe happy they, that did command,</l>
                  <l>And with their feet trod on ſo rich a land,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pſyche</hi> amaz'd, fixt her delighted eye,</l>
                  <l>On the magnificence, and treaſury,</l>
                  <l>And wondred moſt, that ſuch a maſſe of wealth</l>
                  <l>Was by no doore, nor guard, preſerv'd from ſtealth:</l>
                  <l>For looking when ſome ſervant ſhould appeare,</l>
                  <l>She onely heard voices attending there,</l>
                  <l>That ſaid, faire Miſtreſſe why are you afraide?</l>
                  <l>All theſe are yours, and we to doe you ayd.</l>
                  <l>Come up into the roomes, where ſhall be ſhowne</l>
                  <l>Chambers all ready furniſht, all your owne:</l>
                  <l>From thence deſcend, and take the ſpiced aire,</l>
                  <l>Or from your bath unto your bed repaire,</l>
                  <l>Whilſt each of vs, that <hi>Eccho</hi> repreſents,</l>
                  <l>Devoyd of all corporeall inſtruments,</l>
                  <l>Shall wake your Miniſter: no Princely fare</l>
                  <l>Shall wanting be, no dilligence, no care,</l>
                  <l>To doe you ſervice. <hi>Pſyche</hi> had the ſence</l>
                  <l>To taſt, and thanke the Gods beneficence:</l>
                  <l>VVhen ſtraight, a mighty golden diſh was brought,</l>
                  <l>Repleat with all the dainties can be thought;</l>
                  <l>And next a bowle was on the table ſet,</l>
                  <l>Fraught with the richeſt Nectar, that ere yet</l>
                  <l>Faire <hi>Hebe</hi> fill'd to <hi>Iuno,</hi> Heavens
Queene,</l>
                  <l>Or <hi>Ganimed</hi> to <hi>Iove;</hi> yet none was
ſeene,</l>
                  <l>Nor creature found to pledge, or to begin,</l>
                  <l>But ſome impulſive ſpirit brought it in.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12481:15"/>
                  <l>The banquet ended, there was heard on high,</l>
                  <l>A conſort of celeſtiall harmony:</l>
                  <l>And Muſick, mixt with ſounds articulate,</l>
                  <l>That <hi>Phoebus</hi> ſelfe might ſtrive to emulate.</l>
                  <l>All pleaſures finiſht, <hi>Pſyche</hi> went to
reſt,</l>
                  <l>But could finde none, becauſe her troubled breaſt</l>
                  <l>Labour'd with ſtrange events, and now the noone</l>
                  <l>Of night began t'approach, and the pale Moone</l>
                  <l>Hid her weake beames, and ſleepe had ſeiz'd all eyes;</l>
                  <l>But Lovers, vext with feares and jealouſies.</l>
                  <l>What female heart, or conſcience ſo ſtrong</l>
                  <l>Through the diſcharge of finne? but yet among</l>
                  <l>So many fancies of her active braine,</l>
                  <l>She muſt a hundred terrours entertaine?</l>
                  <l>And more, and greater her amazements were,</l>
                  <l>Becauſe ſhe knew not, what ſhe was to feare.</l>
                  <l>In came her dreadfull husband, ſo conceiv'd,</l>
                  <l>Till his ſweet voyce told her, ſhe was deceiv'd,</l>
                  <l>For drawing neare, he ſate upon the bed,</l>
                  <l>Then laid his gentle hand upon her head,</l>
                  <l>And next embrac'd, and kiſt, and did imbrew</l>
                  <l>Her balmy lips with a delicious dew:</l>
                  <l>So, ſo, ſayes he, let each give up his treaſure,</l>
                  <l>Quite bankrupt through a rich exchange of pleaſure.</l>
                  <l>So lets ſweet <hi>Loves preludiums</hi> begin,</l>
                  <l>My armes ſhall be thy Spheare to wander in,</l>
                  <l>Circled about with ſpells, to charme thy feares.</l>
                  <l>Inſtead of <hi>Morpheus</hi> to provoke thy teares,</l>
                  <l>With horrid dreames, <hi>Venus</hi> ſhall thee entrance</l>
                  <l>With thouſand ſhapes of wanton dalliance:</l>
                  <l>Each of thy ſenſes thou ſhalt perfect find,</l>
                  <l>All but thy ſight, for <hi>Love</hi> ought to be blind.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12481:16"/>
                  <l>And having ſaid ſo, he made haſte to bed.</l>
                  <l>Enjoy'd his ſpouſe, and got her Maydenhead:</l>
                  <l>And leaſt that ſhe his feature ſhould diſcloſe,</l>
                  <l>He went away before the morning roſe:</l>
                  <l>Her vocall ſervants watching at the dore,</l>
                  <l>With their mild whiſpers enterd in before</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pſyche</hi> awak't, and joy'd the bride to ſee,</l>
                  <l>And cheer'd her for her ſhine virginity.</l>
                  <l>Theſe things being acted in continued time,</l>
                  <l>And as all humane natures doe incline</l>
                  <l>To take delight by cuſtome, <hi>Pſyche</hi> ſo</l>
                  <l>With theſe aëreall comforts eas'd her woe:</l>
                  <l>But yet her Parents with unwearied griefe</l>
                  <l>Waxt old in teares, and hated all reliefe.</l>
                  <l>Her Siſters too forſooke their houſe, and home,</l>
                  <l>And came to adde unto their fathers moane.</l>
                  <l>That night her husband <hi>Pſyche</hi> thus beſpake,</l>
                  <l>Alas ſweet heart, what comfort can I take,</l>
                  <l>That ſpend the day in ſighes, when you are gone,</l>
                  <l>Rob'd of all humane converſation:</l>
                  <l>My undiſtinguiſht friends are baniſht quite,</l>
                  <l>That almoſt weepe their eyes out for my ſight,</l>
                  <l>Not one of all to beare me company:</l>
                  <l>O let me ſee my ſiſters, or I dye.</l>
                  <l>Her husband her imbrac'd, and kiſt away</l>
                  <l>Thoſe hurtfull teares, and thus began to ſay:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pſyche</hi> my ſweet, and deareſt wife, I ſee,</l>
                  <l>Fortune beginnes to threat thy miſery.</l>
                  <l>What envious Fate ſuggeſts this banefull boone,</l>
                  <l>To force my griefe, and thy deſtruction?</l>
                  <l>Thy ſiſters both, through their vaine fancies led,</l>
                  <l>And troubled with the thought that thou art dead,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12481:16"/>
                  <l>VVill ſeek thee forth: but if thou ſhouldſt regard</l>
                  <l>Their fruit leſſe teares, or ſpeake to them a word,</l>
                  <l>Or by their wicked counſell ſeeke to pry</l>
                  <l>With ſacrilegious curioſity,</l>
                  <l>And view my ſhape, how quickly wouldſt thou throw</l>
                  <l>Thy ſelfe downe headlong to the depth of woe?</l>
                  <l>Thy wretched ſtate for ever to deplore,</l>
                  <l>Nor muſt thou hope to touch me any more.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pſyche</hi> regardleſſe, what his love, or
feares</l>
                  <l>Did prompt unto her good, ſtill perſeveres</l>
                  <l>In her raſh vote: for all (though to their coſt)</l>
                  <l>Deſire forbidden things; but women moſt.</l>
                  <l>My honey husband, my ſweet love, quoth ſhe,</l>
                  <l>How doe I prize thee, whatſoere thou be?</l>
                  <l>Above my ſoule, more then my owne deare life:</l>
                  <l>Nor would I change to be young <hi>Cupids</hi> wife.</l>
                  <l>And rather vow'd a thouſand deaths to dye,</l>
                  <l>Then live divorc'd from his ſociety.</l>
                  <l>Her husband overcome through his owne fire,</l>
                  <l>VVhich her impreſſive kiſſes did inſpire:</l>
                  <l>Gives way to his new ſpouſe, and a ſtrict charge</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Zephirus,</hi> that he ſhould ſpread at large</l>
                  <l>His plumy ſayles, and bring her ſiſters twaine,</l>
                  <l>Both ſafe in preſence of his wife, in paine,</l>
                  <l>To be in priſon, and ſtrict durance bound,</l>
                  <l>VVith the earths weighty fetters under ground,</l>
                  <l>And a huge mountaine to be laid upon</l>
                  <l>His ayerie backe, which if it once were done,</l>
                  <l>No power could e're redeeme his liberty,</l>
                  <l>Nor <hi>Aeolus</hi> himſelfe might ſet him free.</l>
                  <l>Lovers commands are ſtill imperious:</l>
                  <l>VVhich made the fierce and haughty <hi>Zephyrus</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12481:17"/>
                  <l>Swell with cloſe indignation, and fret</l>
                  <l>To ſee his ſervice ſlighted ſo, but yet</l>
                  <l>Not daring to proclaime his diſcontent,</l>
                  <l>Made a ſoft noiſe, and murmur'd as he went.</l>
                  <l>By chance her ſiſters at that inſtant time,</l>
                  <l>With long laborious ſteps the Hill did clime,</l>
                  <l>Where <hi>Pſyche</hi> firſt was left, and with their
plaine,</l>
                  <l>Waken the rocks, ſtill they reſult againe.</l>
                  <l>Calling their ſiſter by her proper name,</l>
                  <l>With hideous cryes, untill the weſt winde came,</l>
                  <l>And as command was, in a winged chaire,</l>
                  <l>With harmeleſſe portage bore them through the aire.</l>
                  <l>All three together by this meanes combin'd,</l>
                  <l>Embrace each other with a mutuall mind.</l>
                  <l>Vntill their ſpirits, and the day was ſpent</l>
                  <l>In long, and ceremonious complement.</l>
                  <l>Sometimes faire <hi>Pſyche,</hi> proud her friends were
by,</l>
                  <l>To witneſſe her majeſtick bravery:</l>
                  <l>Vſhering her ſiſters with affected gate,</l>
                  <l>VVould ſhew them all her glory, and her ſtate,</l>
                  <l>And round about her golden houſe diſplay</l>
                  <l>The maſſie wealth that unregarded lay.</l>
                  <l>Sometimes ſhe would demonſtrate to their cares</l>
                  <l>Her eaſie power on thoſe familiars,</l>
                  <l>That like a numerous family did ſtand,</l>
                  <l>To execute the charge of her command.</l>
                  <l>Nor was there wanting any thing, that might</l>
                  <l>Procure their admiration, or delight:</l>
                  <l>That whereas erſt they pittied her diſtreſſe,</l>
                  <l>Now ſwell with envy of her happineſſe.</l>
                  <l>There is a Goddeſſe flyes through the earths globe</l>
                  <l>Girt with a cloud, and in a ſqualid robe,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12481:17"/>
                  <l>Daughter to <hi>Pluto,</hi> and the ſilent night,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe direfull preſence does the <hi>Sun</hi>
affright:</l>
                  <l>Her name is <hi>Ate,</hi> venome is her food,</l>
                  <l>The very Furies and <hi>Tartarian</hi> brood</l>
                  <l>Doe hate her for her uglineſſe, ſhe blacks</l>
                  <l>Her horrid viſage with ſo many <hi>Snakes,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And as her treſſes 'bout her necke ſhe hurles,</l>
                  <l>The Serpents hiſſe within their knotty curles.</l>
                  <l>Sorrow, and ſhame, death, and a thouſand woes,</l>
                  <l>And diſcord waites her, where ſo ere ſhe goes,</l>
                  <l>Who riding on a whirle wind through the sky,</l>
                  <l>The ſaw faire <hi>Pſyche</hi> in her jollity,</l>
                  <l>And grudg'd to ſee it; for ſhe does profeſſe</l>
                  <l>Her ſelfe a foe, to every good ſucceſſe:</l>
                  <l>Then caſt to ruine her; but found no way,</l>
                  <l>Leſſe ſhe could make her ſiſters her betray,</l>
                  <l>Then cropt foure <hi>Snakes</hi> out of her hayry neſt,</l>
                  <l>And as they ſlept, caſt two on eithers breſt;</l>
                  <l>Who peircing through their boſomes in a trice,</l>
                  <l>Poyſon'd their ſoules, but made no Orifice:</l>
                  <l>And all this while the powerfull bane did lurke</l>
                  <l>VVithin their hearts, and now began to worke:</l>
                  <l>For one of them, too farre inquiſitive,</l>
                  <l>VVith crafty malice did begin to dive</l>
                  <l>Into her councell, ſtudious for to learne,</l>
                  <l>Whom ſo divine poſſeſſions might concerne:</l>
                  <l>But all in vaine, no lineall reſpect,</l>
                  <l>No <hi>Syren</hi> charmes, might move her to reject</l>
                  <l>His precepts; nothing they could doe, or ſay,</l>
                  <l>Might tempt her, his ſweet councell to betray:</l>
                  <l>Yet leaſt too much ſuſpence of what he is,</l>
                  <l>Should trouble their looſe thoughts, ſhe told them
this,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12481:18"/>
                  <l>He was a faire young man, whoſe downy chin,</l>
                  <l>Was newly deckt with natures coverin,</l>
                  <l>And that he vſ'd with hunting ſtill to rome</l>
                  <l>About the woods, and ſeldome was at home,</l>
                  <l>But fearing their diſcourſe might her entrap,</l>
                  <l>She poures forth gold, and jewels in their lapp,</l>
                  <l>And turning all their travell to their gaine,</l>
                  <l>Commands the winds to beare them backe againe.</l>
                  <l>This done, her ſiſters after their returne,</l>
                  <l>With envies fuell, both begin to burne</l>
                  <l>Vnable to containe their diſcontent,</l>
                  <l>And to their ſwell'd up malice give a vent.</l>
                  <l>Sayes one unto the other, what's the cauſe,</l>
                  <l>That we both priviledg'd by natures lawes,</l>
                  <l>And of the ſelfe ſame parents both begot,</l>
                  <l>Should yet ſuſtaine ſuch an indifferent lot?</l>
                  <l>You know, that we are like to handmaides wed</l>
                  <l>To ſtrangers, and like ſtrangers baniſhed.</l>
                  <l>When ſhe, the off ſpring of a latter birth,</l>
                  <l>Sprung from a wombe, that like the tyred earth</l>
                  <l>Grew old with beating; nor yet very wiſe,</l>
                  <l>Enjoyes that wealth, whoſe uſe, whoſe worth and
prize</l>
                  <l>She knowes not, what rich furniture there ſhone,</l>
                  <l>What Gemmes, what gold, what ſilkes we trod upon?</l>
                  <l>And if her husband bee ſo brave a man</l>
                  <l>As ſhe affirmes, and beaſts; what woman can</l>
                  <l>In the whole world compare with her? at length</l>
                  <l>Perhaps by cuſtomes progreſſe, and the ſtrength</l>
                  <l>Of Love, he may her like himſelfe tranſlate</l>
                  <l>And make her with the Gods participate:</l>
                  <l>She has already for to come, and goe</l>
                  <l>Voyces her handmaids, and the winds, 'tis ſo;</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12481:18"/>
                  <l>She bore her ſelfe with no leſſe Majeſty,</l>
                  <l>And breath'd out nothing but Divinity:</l>
                  <l>But I poore wretch, the more to aggravate</l>
                  <l>My cares, and the iniquity of fate,</l>
                  <l>Have got a Husband, elder then my Sire,</l>
                  <l>And then a boy farre weaker in deſire;</l>
                  <l>Who though he have nor will, nor power, to uſe</l>
                  <l>What he enjoyes, does miſer like refuſe;</l>
                  <l>To his owne wife this benefit to grant,</l>
                  <l>That others ſhould ſupply, his, and my want:</l>
                  <l>Her Siſter anſwers, doe not I embrace</l>
                  <l>A man farre worſe, and is't not my owne caſe?</l>
                  <l>I have a husband to, not worth a poynt,</l>
                  <l>And one, that has the Gout in every joynt:</l>
                  <l>His Noſe is dropping, and his eyes are gumm'd,</l>
                  <l>His Body crooked, and his Fingers numm'd,</l>
                  <l>His Head, which ſhould of wiſedome be the place,</l>
                  <l>Is growne more Bald, than any Looking-glaſſe;</l>
                  <l>That I am faine the part to undergoe,</l>
                  <l>Not of a wife, but a Phyſition to;</l>
                  <l>Still plying him, howere my ſenſe it loathes:</l>
                  <l>With Oyles and Balmes, and cataplaſmes and cloaths,</l>
                  <l>Yet you ſee, with what patience I endure</l>
                  <l>This ſervile office, and this fruitleſſe cure,</l>
                  <l>The whilſt the minkes our Siſter, you beheld</l>
                  <l>VVith how great pride, and arrogance, ſhe ſwell'd,</l>
                  <l>And though much wealth lay ſcatter'd all along,</l>
                  <l>Yet out of it, how ſmall a portion</l>
                  <l>She gave to us, and how unwillingly,</l>
                  <l>Then blew, or hiſt us from her company.</l>
                  <l>Let me not breath, nor me a woman call,</l>
                  <l>Vnleſſe I ſtraight her ruine, or enthrall</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12481:19"/>
                  <l>In everlaſting miſery: and firſt</l>
                  <l>In this one poynt, i'll render her accurſt.</l>
                  <l>We will not any into wonder draw,</l>
                  <l>Nor comfort, by relating what we ſaw;</l>
                  <l>For they can not be ſaid true joy to owne,</l>
                  <l>VVhoſe neither wealth, nor happineſſe is knowne.</l>
                  <l>It is enough, that we have ſeene and greive,</l>
                  <l>That we have ſeene it, let none elſe beleive</l>
                  <l>The truth from our report. So lets repaire</l>
                  <l>To our owne home, and our owne homely fare,</l>
                  <l>And then returne, to vindicate her pride,</l>
                  <l>With fraud and malice, ſtrongly fortifi'd:</l>
                  <l>VVhich to confirme, ungratefull as they were,</l>
                  <l>(For wicked councell ever is moſt deare</l>
                  <l>To wicked people,) home againe they drew,</l>
                  <l>And their fayn'd griefe moſt impiouſly renew.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>The Third Section.</head>
                  <l>BY this faire <hi>Pſyches</hi> wombe began to breed,</l>
                  <l>And was made pregnant with immortall ſeed;</l>
                  <l>Yet this condition was on her impoſ'd,</l>
                  <l>That it ſhould mortall prove, if ſhe diſcloſ'd</l>
                  <l>Her husbands councels: who can now relate</l>
                  <l>The joy that ſhe conceiv'd, to propagate</l>
                  <l>A Divine birth? ſhe reckons every day,</l>
                  <l>And weeke, and moneth, and does her wombe ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vay;</l>
                  <l>And wonders ſince ſo little was inſtill'd</l>
                  <l>So ſmall a Veſſell ſhould ſo much be fill'd:</l>
                  <l>Her husband ſmelling of her ſiſters drift,</l>
                  <l>Began to call faire <hi>Pſyche</hi> unto ſhrift,</l>
                  <l>And warne her thus, the utmoſt day ſayes he,</l>
                  <l>And lateſt chance is now befalne to thee;</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12481:19"/>
                  <l>A ſexe pernitious of thine owne deare blood,</l>
                  <l>Has taken armes up to withſtand thy good.</l>
                  <l>Againe thy ſiſters with regardleſſe care</l>
                  <l>Of love, or piety, come to enſnare,</l>
                  <l>And tempt thy faith, which I forbad before,</l>
                  <l>That thou my ſhape, and viſage ſhouldſt explore.</l>
                  <l>In liew of which, take up a like defence,</l>
                  <l>Protecting with religious continence,</l>
                  <l>Our houſe from ruine, and thy ſelfe prevent,</l>
                  <l>And our ſmall pledge from dangers imminent.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pſyche</hi> with ſighes, and teares together
blent,</l>
                  <l>Breaks off his ſpeech, ſince you a document</l>
                  <l>Have of my ſilence, and my love, quoth ſhe,</l>
                  <l>Why ſhould you feare to truſt my conſtancy?</l>
                  <l>Which to confirme, bid <hi>Zephirus</hi> fulfill</l>
                  <l>Once more his duty, and obey ray will.</l>
                  <l>That ſince your long'd for ſight I am deny'd,</l>
                  <l>I may behold my ſiſters by my ſide.</l>
                  <l>Turne not away ſweet love, I thee beſeeke,</l>
                  <l>By thy curl'd haire, and by thy filken cheeke:</l>
                  <l>Deigne from thy bounty, this ſmall boone to ſpare,</l>
                  <l>Since the forc'd ignorance of what you are,</l>
                  <l>Muſt not offend me, nor the darkeſt night,</l>
                  <l>Where I embrace in you a greater light.</l>
                  <l>Charm'd with her ſugred words, he gives conſent,</l>
                  <l>That the ſwift wind, with haſt incontinent;</l>
                  <l>Although unwilling, ſhould diſplay his wing,</l>
                  <l>And the ſhe traytors to faire <hi>Pſyche</hi> bring.</l>
                  <l>Thus altogether met, her ſiſters twaine,</l>
                  <l>Embrace their prey, and a falſe love doe faine.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pſyche,</hi> ſayes one, you are a mother growne:</l>
                  <l>My thinks your wombe like a full Roſe is blowne.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12481:20"/>
                  <l>O what a maſſe of comfort will accrew</l>
                  <l>Vnto our friends, and family from you?</l>
                  <l>Certs this your child, if it be halfe ſo faire</l>
                  <l>As is the mother, muſt be <hi>Cupids</hi> heire.</l>
                  <l>Thus they with flatteries, and with many a ſmile,</l>
                  <l>Pretending falſe affection, her beguile.</l>
                  <l>And ſhe out of her innocence, poore mayd,</l>
                  <l>Gave eaſie credit unto all they ſayd:</l>
                  <l>And too too kind, to a faire chamber led,</l>
                  <l>Where with celeſtiall dainties ſhee them fed.</l>
                  <l>Shee ſpeaks but to the Lute, and ſtraight it heares;</l>
                  <l>Shee calls for raptures, and they ſwell their cares.</l>
                  <l>All ſorts of Muſick ſound, with many a lay,</l>
                  <l>Yet none was preſent ſeene, to ſing or play.</l>
                  <l>But as no mirth is pleaſant to a dull</l>
                  <l>And heavy ſoule, no leſſe, they that are full</l>
                  <l>Of cankred malice, all delight diſdaine,</l>
                  <l>But what does nouriſh their beloved paine.</l>
                  <l>So that no gifts, nor price might mollifie,</l>
                  <l>Nor no rewards, nor kindneſſe qualifie</l>
                  <l>Their hardned hearts, but ſtill they are on fire,</l>
                  <l>To ſound her through, and make a ſtrict inquire,</l>
                  <l>What was her husband, what his forme, and age,</l>
                  <l>And whence he did deduce his parentage:</l>
                  <l>You read, how from ſimplicity at firſt,</l>
                  <l>Shee fram'd a formall ſtory, and what erſt</l>
                  <l>She told, ſhe had forgot, and gan to faine</l>
                  <l>Another tale, and of another ſtraine:</l>
                  <l>How that he was a man both rich, and wiſe,</l>
                  <l>Of middle yeeres, and of a middle ſize:</l>
                  <l>A Merchant by profeſſion, that did deale</l>
                  <l>For many thouſands in the Common-weale.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12481:20"/>
                  <l>With that they checkt her in the full careere</l>
                  <l>Of her diſcourſe; ſayes one, nay ſiſter deare,</l>
                  <l>Pray doe not ſtrive thus to impoſe upon</l>
                  <l>Your loving friends, ſure this deſcription</l>
                  <l>Muſt to his perſon needs be contrary,</l>
                  <l>When in it ſelfe your ſpeech does diſagree.</l>
                  <l>You lately boaſted, hhe was young, and faire;</l>
                  <l>What does the ſoyle, or nature of the aire</l>
                  <l>Bring age ſo ſoone? and that he us'd to range</l>
                  <l>About the woods, loe there's another change.</l>
                  <l>Doe you conceit ſo ignorantly of us,</l>
                  <l>VVe know not <hi>Tethis,</hi> from <hi>Hippolitus?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Greene fields from ſeas, a billow from a hill,</l>
                  <l>Fiſhes from beaſts; then we had little skill.</l>
                  <l>You much diſſemble, or you have forgot</l>
                  <l>His forme, and function, or you know them not.</l>
                  <l>Then with the preſſure of her eyes, ſhee freed</l>
                  <l>One teare from priſon, and did thus proceed:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pſyche</hi> we grieve, and pitty you, that thus</l>
                  <l>Are growne ſo careleſſe, and incurious</l>
                  <l>Of what you ought to feare: you thinke your ſelfe</l>
                  <l>Much happy in your husband, and your ſelfe,</l>
                  <l>But are deceiv'd; for we, that alwayes watch,</l>
                  <l>And at each opportunity doe catch,</l>
                  <l>To ſatisfie our doubts, for truth have found,</l>
                  <l>Both by his crawling footſteps on the ground,</l>
                  <l>And by report of neighbouring husbandmen,</l>
                  <l>That have eſpy'd him flying from his den.</l>
                  <l>VVhen he to them moſt hideouſly has yeeld,</l>
                  <l>From his huge throat, with blood and poyſon ſwell'd,</l>
                  <l>That this your husband is of Serpent breed,</l>
                  <l>Eyther of <hi>Cadmus,</hi> or of <hi>Hydra's</hi> ſeed.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12481:21"/>
                  <l>Call but the <hi>Pythian</hi> Oracle to minde.</l>
                  <l>That you to ſuch hard deſtiny aſſign'd;</l>
                  <l>And thinke not all your art, or policy,</l>
                  <l>Can cancell his propheticall decree.</l>
                  <l>Let not this Monſters uſage for awhile,</l>
                  <l>Your ſoule of juſt ſuſpicion beguile.</l>
                  <l>As that you ſtill ſhall live at ſuch high rate,</l>
                  <l>And that theſe happy dayes ſhal ne're have date.</l>
                  <l>Far be it, that my words ſhould ill portend,</l>
                  <l>Yet truſt me, all theſe joyes muſt have an end:</l>
                  <l>The time will come, when this your Paramour,</l>
                  <l>In whom you ſo delight, ſhall you devoure.</l>
                  <l>And when your womb caſts her abortive brood,</l>
                  <l>Then <hi>Saturne</hi> like, he will make that his food.</l>
                  <l>For this prediction alſo bore a ſhare,</l>
                  <l>In what the god fore-told, but leſt deſpaire</l>
                  <l>Should load you with too great oppreſſion,</l>
                  <l>It was conceal'd, and therefore ſtands upon,</l>
                  <l>Whether through our advice, you will be ſav'd,</l>
                  <l>Or in his beaſtly entrayles be engrav'd.</l>
                  <l>Now if this uncouth life, and ſolitude</l>
                  <l>Pleaſe you, then follow it, and be ſtill ſtew'd</l>
                  <l>In the ranke luſt of a laſcivious worme:</l>
                  <l>Yet we our pious duties ſhall performe.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pſyche</hi> that tender was, grew wan, and pale,</l>
                  <l>And ſwoone for dread of this ſo ſad a tale.</l>
                  <l>Then fell ſhe from the ſpheare of her right mind,</l>
                  <l>And forgot all thoſe precepts ſhe combin'd,</l>
                  <l>And vow'd to keepe, and her ſelfe headlong threw</l>
                  <l>Into a thouſand griefes, that muſt enſue.</l>
                  <l>At laſt reviv'd, having her ſelfe up heav'd,</l>
                  <l>With fainting voyce, thus half her words out breathd.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12481:21"/>
                  <l>Truely my ſiſters deare, full well I ſee</l>
                  <l>How you perſiſt in conſtant piety:</l>
                  <l>Nor did they, who ſuggeſt ſuch words as theſe,</l>
                  <l>In my opinion altogether leaſe:</l>
                  <l>For to this houre, I never did ſurvay</l>
                  <l>My husbands ſhape, but forc'd am to obay</l>
                  <l>What he commands, and doe embrace i'th night,</l>
                  <l>A thing uncertaine, and that ſhunnes the light:</l>
                  <l>Therefore to your aſſertious I aſſent,</l>
                  <l>That with good reaſon ſeeme ſo congruent,</l>
                  <l>For in my thoughts I cannot judge at leaſt</l>
                  <l>But he muſt be a monſter, or ſome beaſt;</l>
                  <l>Hee uſes ſo much cautionary care,</l>
                  <l>And threatens ſo much ill, if I ſhould dare</l>
                  <l>To view his face; ſo I referre me to</l>
                  <l>Your beſt advice, t'inſtruct me what to doe:</l>
                  <l>Her ſiſters now ariv'd at the full ſcope</l>
                  <l>Of their baſe plots, and ſeeing the gate ope</l>
                  <l>That kept her heart, ſcorne any artfull bayt,</l>
                  <l>But uſe their downe right weapons of deceit:</l>
                  <l>Saying, deare <hi>Pſyche,</hi> nature ſhould prevaile</l>
                  <l>So much with us, if miſchiefe did aſſaile</l>
                  <l>Your perſon, in our ſight: we were too blame</l>
                  <l>Should we permit, and not divert the ſame;</l>
                  <l>Yet wiſe men have their waies, and eyes ſtill cleare,</l>
                  <l>And leave no miſts of danger, or of feare:</l>
                  <l>You doe but brave your death, when you repell</l>
                  <l>The whiſpers of your Genius, which would tell</l>
                  <l>The perill you are in; nor are you ſure</l>
                  <l>Of longer life, till you are quite ſecure:</l>
                  <l>Which to effect, provide a ſword that's keene,</l>
                  <l>And with it, a bright Lampe, and both unſeene</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12481:22"/>
                  <l>Hide in ſome place, untill a fitting houre</l>
                  <l>Shall call them, to aſſiſt you with their power:</l>
                  <l>Truſt me, ſuch ſpies, and counſellors are mute,</l>
                  <l>And never nice, or ſlow to execute</l>
                  <l>Any deſigne; ſo when your husbands eyes</l>
                  <l>Are ſeal'd with ſleepe, from your ſoft couch
ariſe,</l>
                  <l>And ſeaze this Dragon, when he leaſt takes heed,</l>
                  <l>Like <hi>Pallas</hi> arm'd, and to his death proceed;</l>
                  <l>And where his necke, and head, are joyn'd in one,</l>
                  <l>Make <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> a
ſpeedy ſeperation:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Alcides</hi> ſonne of <hi>Iove,</hi> as rumour goes,</l>
                  <l>Strangled two <hi>Serpents</hi> in his ſwadling
cloathes:</l>
                  <l>And can your ſtrength faile to bring that to paſſe,</l>
                  <l>Which halfe the labour of an infant was?</l>
                  <l>Such wicked words they poure into her eare,</l>
                  <l>More poyſonous then her husband could appeare.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pſyche</hi> was troubled, as the ſea, in mind</l>
                  <l>Approv'd their councell, and againe declin'd</l>
                  <l>What they perſwade; now haſtens, now delayes,</l>
                  <l>Dares, and not dares, and with a bluſh betrayes</l>
                  <l>Her wandring paſſion, which knowes no meane,</l>
                  <l>But travels from extreame, unto extreame:</l>
                  <l>She loves him now, and does againe deteſt,</l>
                  <l>Loves as a husband, hates him as a beaſt.</l>
                  <l>The onely checke, and bridle to her hate,</l>
                  <l>Was the fam'd ſtory, and revengefull fate</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Danans</hi> daughtets, who in hell are bound</l>
                  <l>To fill a Veſſell, they can never ſound:</l>
                  <l>She told the ſtory to them, how all theſe</l>
                  <l>Were fifty Virgins, call'd the <hi>Belides;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Her Siſters liſt, while <hi>Pſyche</hi> does
diſcover,</l>
                  <l>How each was too inhumane to her lover:</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12481:22"/>
                  <l>And in on night made all their husbands bleed;</l>
                  <l>With hearts, hard as the ſteele, that did the deed:</l>
                  <l>Yet one ſayes ſhe, moſt worthy of the name</l>
                  <l>Of wife, and to it everlaſting fame:</l>
                  <l>Hight <hi>Hypermneſtra,</hi> with officious lye,</l>
                  <l>Met with her Father; and his perjury:</l>
                  <l>Who ſaid unto her husband, youth ariſe,</l>
                  <l>Leaſt a long ſleepe unfear'd, doe thee ſurprize.</l>
                  <l>I will not hold thee captive, nor will ſtrike</l>
                  <l>This to thy heart; although my ſiſters, like</l>
                  <l>So many cruell <hi>Lyoneſſes,</hi> voyd</l>
                  <l>Of mercy, all their husbands have deſtroy'd.</l>
                  <l>I am of nature ſoft, nor doe I dare</l>
                  <l>To view, much leſſe to act thy maſſacre;</l>
                  <l>What though my Father me in priſon lay,</l>
                  <l>Or loade with Iron chaines, or ſend away</l>
                  <l>Farre from his Kingdome, into baniſhment,</l>
                  <l>Or tortures uſe, cauſe I would not conſent</l>
                  <l>To murder thee; however take thy flight,</l>
                  <l>Poſt for thy life, whilſt <hi>Venus</hi> and the night</l>
                  <l>Doe fauour thee, and onely this vouchſafe</l>
                  <l>VVhen I am dead, to write my Epitaph:</l>
                  <l>The meere remembrance of this vertuous deed,</l>
                  <l>Did a remorce, and kind of pitty breed</l>
                  <l>In <hi>Pſyches</hi> breſt, for paſſions are
infuſ'd,</l>
                  <l>According to the ſtories, we are uſ'd</l>
                  <l>To reade; and many men doe amorous prove,</l>
                  <l>By viewing acts, and monuments of loue:</l>
                  <l>But yet her ſiſters malice, that ſtill ſtood</l>
                  <l>In oppoſition, againſt all thats good,</l>
                  <l>Ceaſes not to precipitate her on,</l>
                  <l>Till they had gain'd this confirmation;</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12481:23"/>
                  <l>To put in act what ere they did deſire,</l>
                  <l>Thus fury like, they did her ſoule inſpire:</l>
                  <l>Night and her husband came, and now the ſport</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Venus</hi> ended, he began to ſnort,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pſyche,</hi> though weake of mind, and body both,</l>
                  <l>Yet urg'd by cruell fate, and her raſh oath,</l>
                  <l>Roſe up to make proviſion for her ſinne;</l>
                  <l>Lye ſtill faire maide, thou mayſt more honour win,</l>
                  <l>And make thy murder glory, not a crime;</l>
                  <l>If thou wouldſt kill thoſe thoughts, that doe
beſlime</l>
                  <l>And knaw upon thy breaſt, and never ceaſe</l>
                  <l>With hiſhing clamours to diſturbe thy peace,</l>
                  <l>When thine owne heart with <hi>Serpents</hi> doth abound;</l>
                  <l>Seeke not without, that may within be found.</l>
                  <l>Yet was ſhe not ſo cruell in her haſt,</l>
                  <l>But ere ſhe kild him, ſhe his lips would taſt,</l>
                  <l>Wiſhing ſhe neede not riſe out from her bed,</l>
                  <l>But that ſhe had the power to kiſſe him dead:</l>
                  <l>Now with her lips ſhe labours all ſhe may,</l>
                  <l>To ſucke his ſoule out, whilſt he ſleeping lay,</l>
                  <l>Till ſhe at laſt through a tranſfuſed kiſſe,</l>
                  <l>Left her owne ſoule, and was inſpir'd with his;</l>
                  <l>And had her ſoule within his body ſtay'd,</l>
                  <l>Till he therein his vertues had convay'd,</l>
                  <l>And all pollution would from thence remove,</l>
                  <l>Then after all her thoughts had beene of love;</l>
                  <l>But ſince ſhe could not both of them retaine,</l>
                  <l>She reſtor'd his, and tooke her owne againe:</l>
                  <l>Sorry, that ſhe was forc'd it to tranſferr,</l>
                  <l>And wiſht though dead, that he might live in her:</l>
                  <l>Then in one hand ſhe held the emu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>our light,</l>
                  <l>And in the other tooke the ſword, ſo bright</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12481:23"/>
                  <l>As 'twould her beauty, and the fire out-ſhine,</l>
                  <l>And ſhe thus arm'd, became more maſculine.</l>
                  <l>But when by friendſhip of the Lampe, her eye</l>
                  <l>Had made a perfect true diſcovery</l>
                  <l>Of all was in the roome, what did ſhe ſee?</l>
                  <l>Object of Love, wonder of Deity.</l>
                  <l>The <hi>god of love</hi> himſelfe, <hi>Cupid</hi> the
faire,</l>
                  <l>Lye ſweetly ſleeping in his golden haire:</l>
                  <l>At this ſo heavenly ſight, the lampy ſpire</l>
                  <l>Encreas'd his flames, and burnt more pure, and higher,</l>
                  <l>The very ſenceleſſe ſacrilegious ſteele,</l>
                  <l>Did a ſtrong vertue from his preſence feele,</l>
                  <l>Which turn'd the edge, poore <hi>Pſyche</hi> all amaz'd,</l>
                  <l>With joy, and wonder on his beauty gaz'd.</l>
                  <l>His necke ſo white, his colour ſo exact,</l>
                  <l>His limbes, that were ſo curiouſly compact:</l>
                  <l>His body ſleeke, and ſmooth, that it might not</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Venus</hi> repent, t'have ſuch a ſonne begot.</l>
                  <l>A bright reflexion and perfumed ſent,</l>
                  <l>Fill'd all the roome with a mixt blandiſhment,</l>
                  <l>Shot from his wings, and at his feete did lye</l>
                  <l>His <hi>bow,</hi> and <hi>arrows,</hi> and his
<hi>armory.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And in this extaſie ſhe thought to hide</l>
                  <l>The curſed ſteele, but in her owne deare fide;</l>
                  <l>And had perform'd it ſure, had not the ſword,</l>
                  <l>Flew from her hand, out of its owne accord.</l>
                  <l>Glanſing on all with eyes unſatisfied,</l>
                  <l>At laſt ſhe his artillery eſpyed.</l>
                  <l>The Quiver was of needle-worke wrought round</l>
                  <l>With trophies of his owne, where <hi>Cupid</hi> crown'd</l>
                  <l>Sate in the midſt, with a Bay-wreath, which he</l>
                  <l>Had proudly pluckt from the <hi>Peneian</hi> tree.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12481:24"/>
                  <l>Next <hi>Venus</hi> and <hi>Adonis,</hi> ſad with paine,</l>
                  <l>The one of <hi>love,</hi> the other of
<hi>diſdaine:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>There <hi>love</hi> in all his borrowed ſhapes was
dreſt,</l>
                  <l>His thefts, and his adulteries expreſt,</l>
                  <l>As Emblemes of <hi>Loves</hi> tryumph; and theſe were</l>
                  <l>Drawne with ſuch lively colours, men would ſweare,</l>
                  <l>That <hi>Laeda</hi> lay within a perfect bower,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Danaes</hi> golden ſtreames, were a true
ſhower.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Saturns</hi> two other ſonnes did ſeeme to throw</l>
                  <l>Their <hi>Tridents</hi> at his feete, and him allow</l>
                  <l>For their Supreme; and there were kneeling by</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Gods, Nymphs,</hi> and all their Geneology</l>
                  <l>Since the firſt <hi>Chaos,</hi> ſaving the abuſe,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Cupids</hi> pride, none could the worke traduce.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pallas</hi> in envy of <hi>Aracknes</hi> skill,</l>
                  <l>Or elſe to curry favour, and fulfill</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Cupids</hi> beheſt, which ſhe durſt not
withſtand,</l>
                  <l>Had fram'd the emulous peece with her owne hand.</l>
                  <l>And there were portray'd more a thouſand loves</l>
                  <l>Beſides himſelfe; the skinnes of Turtle-doves</l>
                  <l>Lin'd it within, and at the upper end,</l>
                  <l>A ſilver plate the Quiver did extend,</l>
                  <l>Full of ſmall holes, where his bright ſhafts did lye;</l>
                  <l>Whoſe plumes were ſtiffe with gummes of
<hi>Araby.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>His Bow was of the beſt, and fineſt Yew</l>
                  <l>That in all <hi>Ida,</hi> or faire <hi>Tempe</hi> grew:</l>
                  <l>Smooth as his cheeke, and checkerd as his wing,</l>
                  <l>And at each end, tipt with a Pearle; the ſtring</l>
                  <l>Drawne from the Optick of a Ladies eye,</l>
                  <l>That whenſoere he ſhoots, ſtrikes harmony.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pſyche</hi> with timorous heed, did ſoftly touch</l>
                  <l>His weapons, leaſt her prophane hand might ſmutch</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12481:24"/>
                  <l>The gloſſe of them: then drew a ſhaft, whoſe head</l>
                  <l>Was wrought of Gold, for ſome are done with Lead,</l>
                  <l>And laid her fingers end upon the Dart,</l>
                  <l>Tempting the edge, untill it caus'd a ſmart:</l>
                  <l>For being pointed ſharpe, it raz'd the skin,</l>
                  <l>'Till drops of blood did trickle from within.</l>
                  <l>She wounded with the poiſon, which it bore,</l>
                  <l>Grew more in love, than ere ſhe was before.</l>
                  <l>Then as ſhe would her ſelfe incorporate,</l>
                  <l>She did her numerous kiſſes equall make</l>
                  <l>Vnto his haires, that with her breath did play,</l>
                  <l>Steept with rich <hi>Nectar,</hi> and <hi>Ambroſia.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Thus being raviſht with exceſſe of joy,</l>
                  <l>With kiſſing, and embracing the ſweet Boy.</l>
                  <l>Loe, in the height of all her jollity,</l>
                  <l>Whether from envy, or from treachery:</l>
                  <l>Or that it had a burning appetite,</l>
                  <l>To touch that ſilken skin, that lookt ſo white,</l>
                  <l>The wicked Lampe, in an unlucky houre,</l>
                  <l>A drop of ſcalding oyle did let downe powre</l>
                  <l>On his right ſhoulder, whence in horrid wiſe</l>
                  <l>A bliſter, like a bubble did ariſe,</l>
                  <l>And boyl'd up in his fleſh, with a worſe fume,</l>
                  <l>Then blood of Vipers, or the <hi>Lernean</hi> ſpume.</l>
                  <l>Neere did the Dog-ſtarre rage with ſo great heate</l>
                  <l>In dry <hi>Apulia,</hi> no <hi>Alcides</hi> ſweat</l>
                  <l>Vnder his ſhirt ſo Cruell oyle, that thou</l>
                  <l>Who of all others haſt the ſmootheſt brow,</l>
                  <l>Shouldſt play the traytor? who had any thing</l>
                  <l>Worſe than thy ſelfe, as fire, or venom'd ſting,</l>
                  <l>Or <hi>Sulphur</hi> blaſted him, ſhouldſt firſt have
came,</l>
                  <l>And with thy powerfull breath ſuckt out the flame.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12481:25"/>
                  <l>For though he be <hi>Loves god,</hi> it were but vaine,</l>
                  <l>To thinke he ſhould be privilidg'd from paine.</l>
                  <l>For we in <hi>Homer</hi> have like wounded read,</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Mars,</hi> and <hi>Venus,</hi> both by
<hi>Diomed.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But for this haynous and audacious fact,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Cupid</hi> among his ſtatutes did enact,</l>
                  <l>Henceforth all lights be baniſht, and exempt,</l>
                  <l>From bearing office in <hi>Loves</hi> government.</l>
                  <l>And in the day, each ſhould his paſſage marke,</l>
                  <l>Or learne to finde his Miſtreſſe in the darke.</l>
                  <l>Sure all the crew of lovers ſhall thee hate,</l>
                  <l>Nor bleſt <hi>Minerva</hi> hold thee conſecrate.</l>
                  <l>When <hi>Cupid</hi> ſaw his counſells open laid,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pſyches</hi> deare faith, and his owne plots
betrayd,</l>
                  <l>He buckled on his wings, away to fly;</l>
                  <l>And had ſhe not caught hold upon his thigh,</l>
                  <l>And hung as an <hi>appendix</hi> of his flight,</l>
                  <l>He queſtionleſſe had vaniſht from her ſight.</l>
                  <l>But as when men are in deepe rivers drown'd,</l>
                  <l>And tane up dead, have their cloſe fingers found,</l>
                  <l>Claſping the weeds; ſo, though her armes were rackt</l>
                  <l>With her more bodies weight, and ſinews crackt,</l>
                  <l>To follow him through the forc'd Element:</l>
                  <l>Yet held ſhe faſt, untill he did relent,</l>
                  <l>And his ambitious wings gan downward ſteere,</l>
                  <l>And ſtoope to earth, with a mild Cancileere.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>The fourth Section.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>THus lighted on the earth, he tooke her wriſt,</l>
                     <l>And wrung it hard, and did her hands untwiſt:</l>
                     <l>And having freed himſelfe, he flew on high,</l>
                     <l>Vnto a <hi>Cypreſſe tree</hi> that grew thereby,</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12481:25"/>
                     <l>And on the utmoſt branches being ſate,</l>
                     <l>He did the matter thus capitulate,</l>
                     <l>Was it for this indeed, for this reward,</l>
                     <l>Thou ſilly girle, that I ſhould diſregard</l>
                     <l>My mothers vowes, her teares, her flatteries?</l>
                     <l>When ſhe, with all the power ſhe might deviſe,</l>
                     <l>Provok't me to thy hurt, and thee aſſign'd</l>
                     <l>In Marriage, to a groome of ſome baſe kind,</l>
                     <l>And loweſt ranke, had not my too much haſt</l>
                     <l>Redeem'd thy ſhame, and my owne worth diſgrac'd;</l>
                     <l>Was it for this I did thy plagues remove,</l>
                     <l>To paine my ſelfe? ſtrike mine owne heart in love,</l>
                     <l>With mine owne ſhaft, that after all this geare,</l>
                     <l>I ſhould no better then a beaſt appeare?</l>
                     <l>For this, wouldſt thou cut off my head, which bore</l>
                     <l>Thoſe eyes, that did thy beauty ſo adore?</l>
                     <l>And yet thou knowſt ungratefull wretch, how I</l>
                     <l>Did with my feares, thy miſcheifes ſtill imply,</l>
                     <l>And every day my cautions did renew,</l>
                     <l>The breach of which thou muſt for ever rue:</l>
                     <l>And each of theſe thy ſiſters, that were guide</l>
                     <l>To thy ill act, ſhall dearely it abide:</l>
                     <l>Yet will I puniſh thee no other way</l>
                     <l>But onely this, I will for ever ſtray</l>
                     <l>Farre from thy fight, and having ſaid ſo, fled,</l>
                     <l>Whilſt ſhe to heare this newes, lay almoſt dead:</l>
                     <l>Yet proſtrate on the ground, her eyes up caſt,</l>
                     <l>Ty'd to his winged ſpeed; untill at laſt,</l>
                     <l>She could no more diſcerne; as <hi>Dido,</hi> then,</l>
                     <l>Or <hi>Ariadne,</hi> by ſome Poets pen,</l>
                     <l>Are fayn'd to grieve; whoſe artfull paſſions flow</l>
                     <l>In ſuch ſweet numbers, as they make their woe</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12481:26"/>
                     <l>Appeare delightfull, telling how unkind</l>
                     <l>Their lovers ſtole away, and the ſame wind,</l>
                     <l>That blew abroad their faith, and oathes before;</l>
                     <l>Then fill'd their ſayles, and how the troubled ſhore</l>
                     <l>Anſwer'd the Ladies groanes, ſo <hi>Pſyche</hi>
faints,</l>
                     <l>And beates her breaſt with pittifull complaints.</l>
                     <l>There ran a River neere, whoſe purling ſtreames,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Hyperion</hi> oft, did with his golden beames</l>
                     <l>Delight to gild, and as it fled along</l>
                     <l>The pleaſant murmurs, mixt with the ſweet ſong</l>
                     <l>Of aged <hi>Swannes,</hi> detayn'd the frequent eare</l>
                     <l>Of many a Nymph, which did inhabit there:</l>
                     <l>Poore <hi>Pſyche</hi> thither went, and from the brim,</l>
                     <l>In ſad deſpaire threw her ſelfe headlong in.</l>
                     <l>The Rivers God; whither 'twere out of feare,</l>
                     <l>Duty, or love, or honour he did beare</l>
                     <l>Her husband; or leaſt her ſpilt blood ſhould
ſtaine</l>
                     <l>His chriſtall current, threw her up againe:</l>
                     <l>But it is thought, he would not let her ſinke,</l>
                     <l>Cauſe <hi>Cupid</hi> oft times would deſcend to
drinke,</l>
                     <l>Or waſh him in the Brooke, and when he came</l>
                     <l>To coole his owne heat, would the floud inflame.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Pan</hi> at that time ſate playing on a reed,</l>
                     <l>Whilſt his rough <hi>Goates</hi> did on the meddowes
feed,</l>
                     <l>And with intentive eyes obſerved all,</l>
                     <l>That to the fayreſt <hi>Pſyche</hi> did befall;</l>
                     <l>Who ſeeing her thus pittiouſly diſtreſt,</l>
                     <l>He ran to take her up, and did the beſt</l>
                     <l>He could to comfort her; faire maid, ſayes he,</l>
                     <l>Though I a ruſtick, and a ſhepheard be,</l>
                     <l>Scorne not for that my counſell, and advice;</l>
                     <l>Nor let my trade become my prejudice,</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12481:26"/>
                     <l>For by the benefit of time well ſpent,</l>
                     <l>I am indued with long experiment:</l>
                     <l>And if I doe conjecture it aright,</l>
                     <l>The cauſe of all this Phrenſie, and diſpight,</l>
                     <l>Which your ſad lookes, and paleneſſe doe imply,</l>
                     <l>With other ſignes in Phyſiognomy,</l>
                     <l>By which wiſe men the truth of <hi>Art</hi> doe prove,</l>
                     <l>And know the ſtate of minds; you are in love.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Now liſt to me, and doe not with fond haſt</l>
                     <l>The ſacred oyle of your lifes taper waſt:</l>
                     <l>Vſe no ſiniſter meanes, to haſten on,</l>
                     <l>But labour to adjourne deſtruction,</l>
                     <l>Caſt not away your ſelfe by too much griefe,</l>
                     <l>But courage take; for care is beauties thiefe:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Cupid</hi> I know, whoſe humour is to ſtrive,</l>
                     <l>Then yeeld, then ſtay, then play the fugitive.</l>
                     <l>Be not diſmayd for that, but ſhew your duty,</l>
                     <l>And above all things doe not ſpoyle your beauty,</l>
                     <l>Hee's delicate, and wanton, prayers may win,</l>
                     <l>And faire demeanure may demerit him,</l>
                     <l>Theſe are the medicines I would have you chuſe,</l>
                     <l>To cure your minds health, and redreſſe abuſe:</l>
                     <l>She gave him thankes, then roſe from where ſhe lay,</l>
                     <l>And having done obeyſance went her way;</l>
                     <l>Thence did ſhe wander on with weary feet,</l>
                     <l>And neither track, nor paſſenger could meet,</l>
                     <l>Vntill at length ſhe found a Kingly roade</l>
                     <l>Which led unto a Palace, where aboade</l>
                     <l>Her eldeſt ſiſter. <hi>Pſyche</hi> enter'd in,</l>
                     <l>Then ſent up newes, how one of her neere kin,</l>
                     <l>Was come to viſite her, returne being made,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Pſyche</hi> was brought before her, each invade</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12481:27"/>
                     <l>The other with embraces, and fulfill</l>
                     <l>A tedious ſcene of countefeit good will.</l>
                     <l>But when they had diſcourſ'd a while together,</l>
                     <l>She askt <hi>Pſyche</hi> the cauſe, that brought her
thither,</l>
                     <l>Who did recount the paſſages, and tell,</l>
                     <l>In order all the ſtory that befell,</l>
                     <l>Which by degrees had ruind her; and laid</l>
                     <l>The blame on their lewd counſell, that betray'd</l>
                     <l>Her innocent ſoule, and her firme faith miſled,</l>
                     <l>To murder her deare husband in his bed:</l>
                     <l>She told how ſhe his certaine death decreed,</l>
                     <l>And how ſhe roſe to execute the deed:</l>
                     <l>She told, how like a <hi>Lyoneſſe</hi> ſhe far'd,</l>
                     <l>And like an armed fury, how ſhe ſtar'd,</l>
                     <l>Or like a blazing comet in the ayre,</l>
                     <l>With fire, and ſword, and with diſſhevell'd haire,</l>
                     <l>She told the trouble, and Epitaſis,</l>
                     <l>When ſhe beheld his Metamorphoſis:</l>
                     <l>A ſpectacle, that raviſht her with joy,</l>
                     <l>A <hi>Serpent</hi> turn'd into a lovely boy,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe young, ſmoth face, might ſpeake him boy or
maid:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Cupid</hi> himſelfe in a ſoft ſlumber lay'd,</l>
                     <l>She told too of the drop of ſcalding oyle,</l>
                     <l>That burnt his ſhoulder, and the heavy coyle</l>
                     <l>He kept, when he awakt, cauſ'd by the ſmart;</l>
                     <l>And how he chid, and how at laſt did part:</l>
                     <l>And for revenge, had threatned in her ſtead,</l>
                     <l>To make her ſiſters partners of his bed,</l>
                     <l>And twixt each word, ſhe let a teare downe fall,</l>
                     <l>Which ſtopt her voyce, and made it muſicall.</l>
                     <l>Thus <hi>Pſyche</hi> at the laſt, finiſht her
ſtory</l>
                     <l>Seaſon'd with ſharpe griefe; and ſweet oratory,</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12481:27"/>
                     <l>Which was as long by her relation made,</l>
                     <l>As might have ſerv'd to ſtuffe an <hi>Iliade.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Such as <hi>Aeneas</hi> unto <hi>Dido</hi> told,</l>
                     <l>Full of adventures, ſtrange, and manifold.</l>
                     <l>Her ſiſter by her lookes great joy did ſhow,</l>
                     <l>Reſolv'd in that, ſhe did her husband know;</l>
                     <l>And therefore heard her out, with much applauſe,</l>
                     <l>And gave great heed, but chiefly to that clauſe</l>
                     <l>VVhere 'twas declar'd, that he her pompe, and ſtate</l>
                     <l>To one of her owne ſiſters would tranſlate.</l>
                     <l>VVhence gathering, that her ſelfe might be his bride,</l>
                     <l>She ſwelld with luſt, with envy, and with pride;</l>
                     <l>And in this heate of paſſion did tranſcend</l>
                     <l>The Rock, where <hi>Zephirus</hi> us'd to attend</l>
                     <l>'To waft her up and downe, and there call'd on</l>
                     <l>Him, that had now forſooke his ſtation.</l>
                     <l>Yet through the vanity of hope made blind,</l>
                     <l>Though then there blew a contrary wind:</l>
                     <l>Invoking <hi>Cupid,</hi> that he would receive</l>
                     <l>Her for his ſpouſe, ſhe did her ſelfe bequeath</l>
                     <l>Vnto a fearefull precipice, and threw</l>
                     <l>Her body headlong downe, whoſe weight it drew</l>
                     <l>Towards the Center; for without ſupport,</l>
                     <l>All heavy matter thither will refort.</l>
                     <l>In this her fall, the hard ſtones by the way,</l>
                     <l>Did greet her limbes with a diſcourteous ſtay:</l>
                     <l>Bruiſing her in that manner, that ſhe dyed,</l>
                     <l>As if that ſhe her Jury had denyed.</l>
                     <l>Her younger ſiſter miſſing thus the chiefe</l>
                     <l>Copartner of her ſorrows, pin'd for griefe.</l>
                     <l>This craggy rocke did overlook the ſea,</l>
                     <l>Where greedy <hi>Neptune</hi> had eate in a bay,</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12481:28"/>
                     <l>And undermining it, much ground did win,</l>
                     <l>Where ſilver-footed <hi>Thetis,</hi> riding in</l>
                     <l>Vpon a bridled Dolphin, did explore,</l>
                     <l>And every tyde her armes ſtretcht on the ſhore,</l>
                     <l>Searching each creeke, and cranny, to augment</l>
                     <l>The confines of her watry regiment.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Whilſt here ſhe ſate within a peerly chaire,</l>
                     <l>And round her all the <hi>Sea-gods</hi> did repaire,</l>
                     <l>To whom her lawes ſhe did preſcribe, by hap,</l>
                     <l>The mangled corps fell full into her lap.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Thetis,</hi> that once a child her ſelfe had
borne,</l>
                     <l>Seeing ſo faire a body, fouly torne,</l>
                     <l>And bleeding freſh, judging ſome raviſher</l>
                     <l>Had done this injury, ſhe did conferre</l>
                     <l>About the cure, and there were many found</l>
                     <l>Whoſe trade in Surgery, could heale a wound,</l>
                     <l>But none that might reſtore to life agen.</l>
                     <l>Such was the envy of the <hi>gods:</hi> for when</l>
                     <l>The ſcatter'd limbes of chaſt <hi>Hippolitus,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Were re-inſpir'd by <hi>Aeſculapius,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And by his <hi>Arts</hi> command together came,</l>
                     <l>And every bone and joynt put into frame:</l>
                     <l>That none with emulous skill, ſhould dare the like,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Iove</hi> him to Hell did with his thunder ſtrike.</l>
                     <l>But though ſhe could not by her power controule</l>
                     <l>The Fates decree, to reunite the ſoule,</l>
                     <l>Into another ſhape ſhe made it paſſe,</l>
                     <l>A doctrine held by old <hi>Pythagoras:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>For ſtripping off her clothes, ſhe made her skin</l>
                     <l>To weare a ſoft, and plumy coverin.</l>
                     <l>Her griſly noſe was hardned to a bill,</l>
                     <l>And at each fingers end grew many a quill.</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12481:28"/>
                     <l>Her armes to pennons turn'd, and ſhe in all</l>
                     <l>Chang'd to a Fowle, which men a Sea-gull call.</l>
                     <l>A Bird of evill nature, and ſet on</l>
                     <l>Much miſchiefe, to whoſe compoſition,</l>
                     <l>A great part of her former malice went,</l>
                     <l>And was the principle ingredient.</l>
                     <l>For being thus transfigur'd, ſtraight ſhe ſwam</l>
                     <l>Into the bottom of the Ocean,</l>
                     <l>Where <hi>Neptune</hi> kept his Court, and preſſing
neere</l>
                     <l>To <hi>Venus</hi> ſeat, ſhe whiſper'd her i'th'
eare,</l>
                     <l>How that her ſonne lay deſperately griev'd,</l>
                     <l>Sicke of a burne he lately had receiv'd,</l>
                     <l>And many by that meanes at her did ſcoffe,</l>
                     <l>And her whole family was ill ſpoken off.</l>
                     <l>For whilſt that ſhe her ſelfe, thus liv'd
recluſe.</l>
                     <l>And he his cloſe adulteries did uſe:</l>
                     <l>No ſport, or pleaſure; no delight, or grace,</l>
                     <l>Friendſhip, nor marriage could find any place.</l>
                     <l>In <hi>Love</hi> no pledge, no harmony in life,</l>
                     <l>But every where confuſion was, and ſtrife.</l>
                     <l>Thus the vile Bird maliciouſly did prate,</l>
                     <l>And <hi>Cupids</hi> credit did calumniate.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Venus</hi> replyd, impatient, and hot,</l>
                     <l>What has my good ſonne then a Miſtreſſe got?</l>
                     <l>Which of the Nymphs, or Muſes is his joy?</l>
                     <l>Who has inveigled the ingenious Boy?</l>
                     <l>VVhich of the Howers, or of the Graces all?</l>
                     <l>None of theſe, ſaid the Bird, but men her call</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Pſyche.</hi> So ſoone as <hi>Venus</hi> heard her
nam'd,</l>
                     <l>O how with indignation ſhe exclaim'd?</l>
                     <l>VVhat my owne beauties rivall, is it ſhe?</l>
                     <l>That plant, that ſucker of my dignity.</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12481:29"/>
                     <l>And I his Bawd? VVith theſe words ſhe aſcended</l>
                     <l>To the Seas <hi>ſuperficies,</hi> where attended</l>
                     <l>Her Doves born ready harneſt, up ſhe got,</l>
                     <l>And flew to <hi>Paphos</hi> in her chariot.</l>
                     <l>The Graces came about her, and in haſt</l>
                     <l>VVhat the rough ſeas, or rude winds had miſplac'd,</l>
                     <l>Did recompoſe with art and ſtudious care,</l>
                     <l>Kembing the Cerule drops from her looſe haire:</l>
                     <l>VVhich dry'd with Rofie powder, they did fold,</l>
                     <l>And bind it round up in a brayd of Gold.</l>
                     <l>Theſe waite about her perſon ſtill, and paſſe</l>
                     <l>Their judgement on her, equall with her glaſſe.</l>
                     <l>Theſe ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> the onely <hi>Criticks,</hi> that debate</l>
                     <l>All beauty, and all faſhions arbitrate:</l>
                     <l>Theſe temper her <hi>Ceruſe,</hi> and paint, and lim</l>
                     <l>Her face with oyle, and put her in her trim.</l>
                     <l>Twelve other Hand maids clad in white array,</l>
                     <l>Call'd the <hi>twelve Houres,</hi> and <hi>daughters of the
day,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Did helpe to dreſſe her: there were added more,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Twelve of the night,</hi> whoſe eyes were ſhadowed
ore</l>
                     <l>VVith dusky, and black vailes, leaſt <hi>Vulcans</hi>
light,</l>
                     <l>Or vapours ſhould offend their bleared ſight,</l>
                     <l>When they her linnen ſtarch, or elſe prepare</l>
                     <l>Strong diſtillations to make her faire.</l>
                     <l>Theſe bring her bathes, and ointments for her eyes,</l>
                     <l>And provide Cordialls, 'gainſt ſhe ſhall ariſe.</l>
                     <l>Theſe play on Muſick, and perfume her bed,</l>
                     <l>And ſnuffe the Candle, while ſhe lyes to read</l>
                     <l>Her ſelfe aſleepe: thus all aſſign'd unto</l>
                     <l>Their ſeverall office, had enough to doe.</l>
                     <l>And had they twenty times as many beene,</l>
                     <l>They all might be imploy'd about the Queene.</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12481:29"/>
                     <l>For though they vſ'd more reverence, then at prayer.</l>
                     <l>And ſate in counſell upon every haire,</l>
                     <l>And every pleat, and poſture of her gowne,</l>
                     <l>Giving obſervance to each frequent frowne.</l>
                     <l>And rather wiſht the ſtate diſordered were,</l>
                     <l>Then the leaſt implement, that ſhe did weare.</l>
                     <l>As if, of all, that were the greateſt ſin,</l>
                     <l>And that their fate were faſtned to each pin:</l>
                     <l>Though their whole life, and ſtudy were to pleaſe,</l>
                     <l>Yet ſuch a ſullen humour, and diſeaſe</l>
                     <l>Raign'd in her curious eyes, ſhe ever ſaught,</l>
                     <l>And ſcowling lookt, where ſhe might find a fault,</l>
                     <l>Yet felt ſhe no diſtemper from the care</l>
                     <l>Of other buſineſſe, nor did any dare</l>
                     <l>To interpoſe, or put into her mind,</l>
                     <l>A thought of any, either foe, or friend,</l>
                     <l>Receipt, or payment, but they all were bent</l>
                     <l>To place each jewell, and each ornament.</l>
                     <l>And when that ſhe was dreſt, and all was done,</l>
                     <l>Then ſhe began to thinke upon her ſonne,</l>
                     <l>And being abſent, ſpake of him at large,</l>
                     <l>And lay'd ſtrong aggravations to his charge.</l>
                     <l>She ript her wrongs up, how ſhe had paſt by,</l>
                     <l>In hope of mendment, many an injury:</l>
                     <l>Yet nothing could reclaime his ſtubborne ſpleene</l>
                     <l>And wanton looſeneſſe, though ſhe ſtill had
beene</l>
                     <l>Indulgent to him, as they all did know.</l>
                     <l>She talkt to of the duty, children owe</l>
                     <l>Vnto their parents, and did much complaine;</l>
                     <l>Since ſhe had bore, and bred him up with paine,</l>
                     <l>Now for requitall, had receiv'd offence;</l>
                     <l>And ſorely taxt his diſobedience,</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12481:30"/>
                     <l>Then askt the Graces, if they could diſcloſe</l>
                     <l>Where his new haunts were, and his Randevous,</l>
                     <l>For, ſhe had truſted them, to over looke</l>
                     <l>As Guardians, and to guide, as with a hooke</l>
                     <l>His ſtragling nature, and they had done ill,</l>
                     <l>To ſlacke their hand, and leave him to his will;</l>
                     <l>Who, as ſhe ſaid, was a weake child, and none</l>
                     <l>Being neere, might ſoo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e into much miſchiefe run.</l>
                     <l>They bluſhing ſmile, and thus alleadg; ſince
ſhe,</l>
                     <l>His Mother could not rule him, how can we</l>
                     <l>That are but Servants<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> whom he does deſpiſe,</l>
                     <l>And brandiſhes his torch againſt our eyes,</l>
                     <l>And in defiance, threats what he will doe,</l>
                     <l>Vpon the leaſt diſtaſt, to ſhoote us through.</l>
                     <l>When <hi>Venus</hi> heard, how the world ſtood in awe</l>
                     <l>Of her ſonnes deſperate valoure, and no law</l>
                     <l>Might curbe his fierceneſſe, flattery, nor force</l>
                     <l>Prevaile, ſhe then reſolv'd upon a courſe,</l>
                     <l>With open libels, and with hue and cry,</l>
                     <l>To publiſh to the world his infamy:</l>
                     <l>And therefore cauſ'd in every towne, and ſtreet,</l>
                     <l>And in all tryviall places, where wayes meet,</l>
                     <l>In theſe words or the like, upon each poſt,</l>
                     <l>A chartell to be fixt, that he was loſt.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The wanton</hi> Cupid, <hi>t'other day,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Did from his mother</hi> Venus <hi>ſtray.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Great paines ſhe tooke, but all in vaine</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>How to get her Sonne againe:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>For ſince the boy is ſometimes blind,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>He his owne way cannot find.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12481:30"/>
                     <l>
                        <hi>If any one can fetch him in,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Or take him captive in a Gin,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And bring her word, ſhe for this,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Will reward him with a kiſſe.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>That you the felon may deſcry,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Theſe are ſignes to know him by:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>His skin is red with many a ſtaine</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Of Lovers, which by him were ſlaine;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Or elſe it is, the fatall doome,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Which foretells of ſtormes to come:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Though he ſeeme naked to the eye,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>His mind is cloath'd with ſubtlety,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Sweet ſpeach he uſes, and ſoft ſmiles,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>To intice where he beguiles:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>His words are gentle, as the ayre,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>But truſt him not, though he ſpeake faire;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And confirme it with an oath:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>He is fierce, and cruell both,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>He is bold, and careleſſe too,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And will play as wantons doe:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>But when you thinke the ſport is paſt,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>It turnes to earneſt at the laſt.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>His evill nature none can tame,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>For neither reverence, nor ſhame,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Are in his lookes; his curled hayre</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Hangs like Nets, for to enſnare.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>His hands though weake, and ſlender; ſtrike</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Age, and Sexes, all alike,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And when he liſt, will make his neſt,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>In their Marrow, or their breaſt:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Thoſe poyſon'd Darts ſhot from his Bow,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Hurt Gods above, and men below.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12481:31"/>
                     <l>
                        <hi>His left hand beares a burning Torch,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Whoſe flame the very ſame will ſcorch;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And not hell it ſelfe is free,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>From this Impes impiety.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The wounds he makes, no Salve can cure;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Then if you catch him, bind him ſure:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Take no pitty, though he cry,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Or laugh, or ſmile, or ſeeme to dye,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And for his ranſome would deliver</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>His Arrowes, and his painted Quiver.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Refuſe them all, for they are ſuch,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>That will burne, where ere they touch.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>When this edict was openly declar'd</l>
                     <l>And <hi>Venus</hi> importunity; none dar'd</l>
                     <l>To be ſo much of counſell, as to hide,</l>
                     <l>And not reveale, where <hi>Cupid</hi> did abide.</l>
                     <l>There was an old Nimph of th' <hi>Idalian</hi> grove,</l>
                     <l>Grand-child to <hi>Faune, a Dryad;</hi> whom great
<hi>Iove</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Had raviſht in her youth, and for a fee,</l>
                     <l>In recompence of her Virginity,</l>
                     <l>Did make Immortall, and with wiſedome fill,</l>
                     <l>And her endewed with a Prophetick skill,</l>
                     <l>And knowledge of all Hearbes; ſhe could apply</l>
                     <l>To every greife a perfect remedy,</l>
                     <l>Were it in mind, or body, and was ſage,</l>
                     <l>And waighty in her counſell, to aſwage</l>
                     <l>Any diſeaſe; ſhe had the government</l>
                     <l>Of the whole Pallace, and was preſident</l>
                     <l>Of all the Nimphs, for <hi>Venus</hi> did commit</l>
                     <l>Such power, to doe; what ever ſhe thought fit.</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12481:31"/>
                     <l>She at that time dreſt <hi>Cupid</hi> for his ſmart,</l>
                     <l>And would have hid his ſhame with all her heart:</l>
                     <l>But that ſhe fear'd her Miſtreſſe to
diſpleaſe,</l>
                     <l>If it ſhould after chance the <hi>Dryades</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Betray'd her; therefore ſhe durſt doe no other,</l>
                     <l>But to ſend private word unto his Mother,</l>
                     <l>Where her ſonne was, and how he hid his head,</l>
                     <l>And groaning lay upon his Mothers bed.</l>
                     <l>Soone as this newes was brought her, <hi>Venus</hi>
went,</l>
                     <l>Blowne with the winde, and her owne diſcontent.</l>
                     <l>And there began to ſcold, and rayle, before</l>
                     <l>She did arrive within the chamber dore.</l>
                     <l>Are theſe things honeſt, which I heare ſayes
ſhe,</l>
                     <l>And ſuiting with our fame and pedegree?</l>
                     <l>Seducing trifler, have you ſet at large</l>
                     <l>Mine enemy, whom I gave up in charge,</l>
                     <l>That thou ſhouldſt captivate, and ſet on fire,</l>
                     <l>With ſordid, but unquenchable deſire?</l>
                     <l>But ſince; that thou mightſt the more ſtubborn
prove,</l>
                     <l>Haſt fetter'd her unto thy ſelfe in love;</l>
                     <l>Seemes you preſume, that you are onely he,</l>
                     <l>The Chick of the white Hen, and ſtill muſt be.</l>
                     <l>And I, by reaſon of my age, quite done,</l>
                     <l>Cannot conceive, nor beare another ſonne.</l>
                     <l>Yes know I can, and for thy more diſgrace,</l>
                     <l>I will adopt another in thy place.</l>
                     <l>I'le take away that wicked ſtuffe, with which</l>
                     <l>Thou doſt abuſe thy betters, and bewitch</l>
                     <l>Each age, and ſexe, and not without delight,</l>
                     <l>Thine Vncle <hi>Mars,</hi> and thine owne Mother
ſmite.</l>
                     <l>Then burne thoſe armes, which were ordain'd to doe</l>
                     <l>Better exploits, then thou imploy'ſt them to.</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12481:32"/>
                     <l>For thou waſt ever from thy youth untoward,</l>
                     <l>And doſt without all reverence, or regard,</l>
                     <l>Provoke thy elders, but <hi>Iove,</hi> here I wiſh,</l>
                     <l>I ne're may eate of a celeſtiall diſh:</l>
                     <l>Vnleſſe I turne this tryumph to offence,</l>
                     <l>This ſweet to ſower, this ſport to penitence.</l>
                     <l>But I thus ſcorned, whither ſhall I fly?</l>
                     <l>There is a Matron call'd <hi>Sobriety,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Whom I have oft offended, through his vaine</l>
                     <l>Luxurious riot, yet I muſt complaine</l>
                     <l>To her, and at her hands expect the full</l>
                     <l>Of my revenge, ſhe ſhall his quiver pull,</l>
                     <l>Vnhead his <hi>arrows,</hi> and his <hi>Bow</hi>
unſtring;</l>
                     <l>Put out his <hi>Torch,</hi> and then away it fling.</l>
                     <l>His golden locks with <hi>Nectar</hi> all imbrewd,</l>
                     <l>Which I from my owne boſome have bedew'd.</l>
                     <l>His various wings, the Raine-bow never yet,</l>
                     <l>Was in ſuch order, nor ſuch colours ſet:</l>
                     <l>She ſhall without remorſe both cut, and pare,</l>
                     <l>And every feather clip, and every haire.</l>
                     <l>And then, and not till then, it ſhall ſuffice,</l>
                     <l>That I have done my wrongs this ſacrifice.</l>
                     <l>Thus full of choler, did ſhe <hi>Cupid</hi> threat,</l>
                     <l>And having eas'd her mind, did backe retreat.</l>
                     <l>But making haſte, with this diſtemper'd looke,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Ceres,</hi> and <hi>Iuno</hi> both, ſhe overtooke:</l>
                     <l>Who ſeeing her with ſuch a troubled brow,</l>
                     <l>Did earneſtly demand, the manner how</l>
                     <l>She came ſo vext, and who had power to ſhrowd</l>
                     <l>Her glorious beauty in ſo black a clowd.</l>
                     <l>You cannot chuſe but heare, <hi>Venus</hi> reply'd,</l>
                     <l>How I have beene abus'd, on every ſide.</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12481:32"/>
                     <l>Firſt, when, my limping husband me beſet,</l>
                     <l>And caught <hi>Mars,</hi> and my ſelfe, both in his
net:</l>
                     <l>And then expos'd us naked to the eyes</l>
                     <l>Of Heaven, and the whole bench of Deities.</l>
                     <l>'Tis a knowne tale; and to make up the jeſt,</l>
                     <l>One <hi>god,</hi> leſſe ſupercilious then the
reſt,</l>
                     <l>Told <hi>Mars,</hi> if thoſe his fetters made him
ſweat,</l>
                     <l>He would endure the burthen, and the heat.</l>
                     <l>Time wore out this diſgrace, but now your art</l>
                     <l>Muſt drive another ſorrow from my heart:</l>
                     <l>And if you love me, uſe your beſt of skill,</l>
                     <l>To ſeeke out <hi>Pſyche,</hi> ſhe hath done this
ill.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Cupid</hi> my ſonne, has choſe her for his
ſpouſe,</l>
                     <l>That is the onely plague vnto my houſe.</l>
                     <l>Lady, ſaid they, alack what hurt is done,</l>
                     <l>Or crime in this committed by your ſonne?</l>
                     <l>Is this a cauſe, fit to provoke your ſpight;</l>
                     <l>T'impugne his ſports, and hinder his delight?</l>
                     <l>What imputation on your houſe were layd,</l>
                     <l>Though he ſhould ſet his fancy on a Maid?</l>
                     <l>You may allow his Patent for to paſſe,</l>
                     <l>That he may love a blith, and bonny Laſſe.</l>
                     <l>What you forget, that he is well in yeeres,</l>
                     <l>And tis a comfort to you, that he beares</l>
                     <l>His age ſo well; therefore you muſt not pry</l>
                     <l>Into his actions ſo narrowly.</l>
                     <l>For with what Juſtice can you diſapprove</l>
                     <l>That in your ſonne, which in your ſelfe you love?</l>
                     <l>Is't fit, that ſeeds of <hi>love</hi> by you be
ſowne</l>
                     <l>In others hearts, and baniſht from your owne?</l>
                     <l>You have an intereſt, in all that's his:</l>
                     <l>Both prais'd for good, both blam'd for what's
amiſſe.</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12481:33"/>
                     <l>Remember too, you are his Mother deare:</l>
                     <l>Held wiſe, and muſt give way: thus they for feare</l>
                     <l>Of <hi>Cupids</hi> Arrowes, did him patronize.</l>
                     <l>But <hi>Venus</hi> ſcorning that her injuries</l>
                     <l>VVere no more pittied, her ſwift Doves did raigne,</l>
                     <l>And took her way towards the Sea againe.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <trailer>The end of the firſt Booke.</trailer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="book">
               <head>The Second Booke.</head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>THE FIRST SECTION.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>
                           <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Syche</hi> this while wandred the world about</l>
                     <l>With various errors to find <hi>Cupid</hi> out,</l>
                     <l>Hoping, although no matrimoniall way,</l>
                     <l>Or Beauties force his anger might allay;</l>
                     <l>Yet Prayers, and duty ſomewhat might a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate,</l>
                     <l>And humble Service him propitiate.</l>
                     <l>She travell'd forth, untill at length ſhe found</l>
                     <l>A pleaſant plaine, with a faire <hi>Temple</hi>
crown'd.</l>
                     <l>Then to her ſelfe ſhe ſaid, ah who can tell,</l>
                     <l>Whether or no, my husband there doe dwell?</l>
                     <l>And with this thought ſhe goes directly on,</l>
                     <l>Led with blind hope, and with Devotion:</l>
                     <l>Then entred in, ſhe to the <hi>Altar</hi> bended,</l>
                     <l>And there perform'd her <hi>Orizons:</hi> which ended,</l>
                     <l>Caſting her eyes about, ſhe did eſpy,</l>
                     <l>A world of inſtruments for husbandry:</l>
                     <l>As Forkes, &amp; Hookes, &amp; Rakes; Sickles, &amp;
Sithes,</l>
                     <l>Garlands, and Sheares, &amp; Corne for Sacrifice.</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12481:33"/>
                     <l>Thoſe eares, that were confuſed, ſhe did ſever,</l>
                     <l>And thoſe, that ſcatter'd lay, ſhe put together;</l>
                     <l>Thinking, ſhe ought no worſhip to decline</l>
                     <l>Of any thing, that ſeem'd to be Divine.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Ceres</hi> farre off did <hi>Pſyche</hi> over
looke,</l>
                     <l>When this laborious taske ſhe undertooke,</l>
                     <l>And as ſhe is a <hi>Goddeſſe,</hi> that does love</l>
                     <l>Induſtrious people, ſpake to her from above;</l>
                     <l>Alas poore <hi>Pſyche, Venus</hi> is thy foe,</l>
                     <l>And ſtrives to find thee out with more a doe,</l>
                     <l>Then I my <hi>Proſerpine;</hi> the Earth, the Sea,</l>
                     <l>And the hid confines of the Night and Day,</l>
                     <l>Have all beene ranſackt; ſhe has ſought thee
forth,</l>
                     <l>Through both the <hi>Poles,</hi> &amp; Mantions of the
North,</l>
                     <l>Not the <hi>Riphean</hi> ſnow, nor all the drougth,</l>
                     <l>That parches the vaſt deſarts of the ſouth,</l>
                     <l>Have ſtay'd her ſteps. She has made <hi>Tethis</hi>
ſweepe,</l>
                     <l>To find thee out, the bottome of the deepe,</l>
                     <l>And vowes that Heaven it ſelfe ſhall thee reſigne,</l>
                     <l>Though <hi>Iove</hi> had fixt thee, there his concubine.</l>
                     <l>She never reſts, for ſince ſhe went to bed,</l>
                     <l>The Roſie Crowne is wither'd from her head:</l>
                     <l>Thou careleſſe wretch. Thus <hi>Venus</hi> all
enrag'd,</l>
                     <l>Seekes for thy life, whilſt thou art heere ingag'd</l>
                     <l>'Bout my affaires, and thinkſt of nothing leſſe,</l>
                     <l>Then thine owne ſafety, and loſt happineſſe.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Pſyche</hi> fell proſtrate on her face, before</l>
                     <l>Faire <hi>Ceres</hi> throne, and did her helpe implore,</l>
                     <l>Moyſtning the Earth with teares, and with her haire</l>
                     <l>Bruſhing the ground; ſhe ſent up many a Prayer,</l>
                     <l>By thy fruit-ſcattering hand, I thee entreate,</l>
                     <l>And the <hi>Sicilian</hi> Feilds, that are the ſeat</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12481:34"/>
                     <l>Of thy fertility, and by the glad,</l>
                     <l>And happy ends, the harveſt ever had;</l>
                     <l>And by thy coach, with winged <hi>Dragons</hi> drawne,</l>
                     <l>And by the darkeſome hell, that gan to dawne</l>
                     <l>At the bright marriage of faire <hi>Proſerpine:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And by the ſilent rites of <hi>Eluſine,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Impart ſome pitty, and vouchſafe to grant</l>
                     <l>This ſmall requeſt, to your poore ſupplyant.</l>
                     <l>I may lye hid among theſe ſheaves of Corne,</l>
                     <l>Vntill great <hi>Venus</hi> fury be out-worne;</l>
                     <l>Or that my ſtrength, and faculties ſubdu'd</l>
                     <l>By weary toyle, a little be renew'd.</l>
                     <l>But as the worlds accuſtom'd, when they ſee,</l>
                     <l>Any orewhelm'd with a deepe miſery,</l>
                     <l>Afford ſmall comfort to their wretched ſtate;</l>
                     <l>But onely are in words compaſſionate.</l>
                     <l>So <hi>Ceres</hi> told her, ſhe did greatly grieve</l>
                     <l>At her diſtreſſe, but durſt her not releive;</l>
                     <l>For <hi>Venus</hi> was a good, and gratious Queene,</l>
                     <l>And ſhe her favour highly did eſteeme.</l>
                     <l>Nor would ſhe ſuccour a contrary ſide,</l>
                     <l>Being by love, and kin to her ally'd.</l>
                     <l>Poore <hi>Pſyche</hi> thus repulſ'd, ſoone as ſhe
ſaw</l>
                     <l>Her hopes quite fruſtrate, did her ſelfe withdraw,</l>
                     <l>And journied on, unto a neighbouring wood,</l>
                     <l>Where likewiſe a rich <hi>Fane,</hi> and <hi>Temple</hi>
ſtood,</l>
                     <l>Of goodly ſtructure, and before the houſe,</l>
                     <l>Hung many gifts, and garments pretious,</l>
                     <l>That by the name engrav'd, and dedication,</l>
                     <l>Expreſt without, to whom they had relation.</l>
                     <l>Here <hi>Pſyche</hi> enterd, her low knees did bend,</l>
                     <l>And both her ſelfe, and fortunes recommend</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12481:34"/>
                     <l>To mighty <hi>Iuno,</hi> and thus ſpake to her.</l>
                     <l>Thou wife, and ſiſter to the thunderer,</l>
                     <l>Whether thou doſt in ancient <hi>Samos</hi> lye,</l>
                     <l>The place of thy firſt birth, and nurſery.</l>
                     <l>Or by the bankes of <hi>Inacus</hi> abide,</l>
                     <l>Or thy lou'd <hi>Carthage;</hi> or round Heaven doſt
ride</l>
                     <l>Vpon a <hi>Lyons</hi> backe; that art i'th Eaſt</l>
                     <l>Call'd <hi>Zigia,</hi> and <hi>Lucina</hi> in the
weſt;</l>
                     <l>Looke on my griefes extremity, and deigne</l>
                     <l>To eaſe me, of ray labour, and my paine.</l>
                     <l>Thus having prayed, ſtraight <hi>Iuno</hi> from on
high,</l>
                     <l>Preſents her ſelfe in all her Majeſty;</l>
                     <l>And ſaid, <hi>Pſyche</hi> I wiſh you had your
ends,</l>
                     <l>And that my Daughter, &amp; your ſelfe were friends:</l>
                     <l>For <hi>Venus</hi> I have ever held moſt deare,</l>
                     <l>In as high place, as ſhe my daughter were:</l>
                     <l>Nor can that, which one <hi>Goddeſſe</hi> has begun,</l>
                     <l>By any other Deity b'undone,</l>
                     <l>Beſides the <hi>Stigian</hi> lawes allow no leave,</l>
                     <l>That we anothers Servant ſhould receive;</l>
                     <l>Nor can we by the league of friendſhip, give</l>
                     <l>Reliefe to one, that is a fugitive.</l>
                     <l>Faire <hi>Pſyche</hi> ſhipwrackt in her hopes
againe,</l>
                     <l>And finding no wayes, how ſhe might obtaine</l>
                     <l>Her winged husband, caſt the worſt of all;</l>
                     <l>And thus her thoughts did into queſtion call:</l>
                     <l>What meanes can be attempted, or apply'd</l>
                     <l>To this my ſtrange calamity, beſide</l>
                     <l>What is already uſ'd? for though they wood,</l>
                     <l>The Gods themſelves, can render me no good,</l>
                     <l>Why then ſhould I proceed, and unawares</l>
                     <l>Tender my foot unto ſo many ſnares?</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12481:35"/>
                     <l>VVhat darkneſſe can protect me? what diſguiſe</l>
                     <l>Hide me from her inevitable eyes?</l>
                     <l>Some women, from their crimes, can courage gather,</l>
                     <l>Then why not I from miſery? and rather,</l>
                     <l>VVhat I cannot deferre, nor long withſtand,</l>
                     <l>Yeeld up my ſelfe a priſoner to her hand.</l>
                     <l>For timely modeſty may mitigate</l>
                     <l>That rage, which abſence does exaſperate.</l>
                     <l>And to confirme this, who knows, whether he,</l>
                     <l>VVhom my ſoule longs for, with his Mother be?</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Venus</hi> now ſicke of earthly buſineſſe,</l>
                     <l>Commands her Coach be put in readineſſe:</l>
                     <l>Whoſe ſubtile ſtructure was all wrought upon,</l>
                     <l>With gold, with purple, and Vermilion.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Vulcan</hi> compos'd the fabrick, 'twas the ſame</l>
                     <l>He gave his wife, when he a woing came.</l>
                     <l>Then of thoſe many hundred Doves, that ſoare</l>
                     <l>About her palace, ſhe ſelected foure,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe checkred necks to the ſmall traces ty'd,</l>
                     <l>With nimble gyres they up to Heaven did glide:</l>
                     <l>A world of ſparrows did by <hi>Venus</hi> fly,</l>
                     <l>And Nightingales, that ſung melodiouſly.</l>
                     <l>And other birds accompany'd her Coach,</l>
                     <l>With pleaſant noiſe, proclaiming her approach:</l>
                     <l>For neither hardy Eagle, Hawke, nor Kite,</l>
                     <l>Durſt her ſweet ſounding family affright.</l>
                     <l>The clouds gave way, and Heaven was open made,</l>
                     <l>Whilſt <hi>Venus, Ioves</hi> high Turrets did invade.</l>
                     <l>Then having ſilenc'd her obſtreperous quire,</l>
                     <l>She boldly calls for <hi>Mercury</hi> the cryer,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Ioves</hi> meſſenger, who but a while before</l>
                     <l>Return'd with a looſe arrant, which he bore.</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12481:35"/>
                     <l>To a new Miſtreſſe, and was now t'adviſe</l>
                     <l>Vpon ſome tricke, to hide from <hi>Iuno's</hi> eyes</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Ioves</hi> bawderie, for he ſuch feats can doe,</l>
                     <l>Which are his vertues, and his office to.</l>
                     <l>When <hi>Venus</hi> ſaw him, ſhe much joy did
ſhow,</l>
                     <l>And ſaid, kind brother <hi>Mercury,</hi> you know,</l>
                     <l>How I eſteeme your love, at no ſmall rate,</l>
                     <l>With whom my minde I ſtill communicate:</l>
                     <l>Without whoſe counſell I have nothing done,</l>
                     <l>But ſtill preferr'd your admonition.</l>
                     <l>And now you muſt aſſiſt me; ther's a mayd</l>
                     <l>Lyes hid, whom I have long time ſought, and layd</l>
                     <l>Cloſe waite to apprehend, but cannot take;</l>
                     <l>Therefore I'de have you proclamation make,</l>
                     <l>With a reward propounded, to requite,</l>
                     <l>Who e're ſhall bring, and ſet her in my ſight.</l>
                     <l>Make knowne her markes, and age, leſt any chance,</l>
                     <l>Or after dare to pretend ignorance.</l>
                     <l>Thus having ſaid, ſhe gave to him a note,</l>
                     <l>And libell, wherein <hi>Pſyches</hi> name was wrote.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Hermes</hi> the powerfull, and all charming
<hi>god</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Taking in hand his ſoule conſtraining rod,</l>
                     <l>VVith which he carries, and brings backe from hell,</l>
                     <l>VVith <hi>Venus</hi> went, for he lov'd <hi>Venus</hi>
well;</l>
                     <l>'Cauſe he in former time her love had wonne,</l>
                     <l>And in his dalliance, had of her ſonne</l>
                     <l>Begot, call'd the <hi>Hermaphrodite,</hi> which is</l>
                     <l>The Boy, that was belov'd by <hi>Salmacis.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Thus both from Heaven deſcended, open cry</l>
                     <l>In expreſſe words, was made by <hi>Mercury,</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>O yes, if any can true tidings bring</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Of</hi> Venus <hi>hand-maid, daughter to a
King,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12481:36"/>
                     <l>Pſyche <hi>the fugitive, of ſtature tall,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Of tender age, and forme celeſtiall:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>To whom, for dowry, Art, and Nature gave</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>All grace, and all the comlineſſe they
have.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>This I was bid to ſay, and be it ſpoken</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Without all envy, each ſmile is a token</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Sufficient to betray her. In her gate</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>She</hi> Phoebus <hi>ſiſter does moſt
imitate.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Nor does her woyce ſound mortall, if you
ſpy</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Her face, you may diſcerne her by the eye,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>That like a ſtarre, dazels the Optick
ſenſe,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Cupid <hi>has oft his Torch brought lighted thence.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>If any finde her out, let him repaire</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Straight wayes to</hi> Mercury, <hi>and the newes
declare;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And for his recompence, he ſhall have leave,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Even from</hi> Venus <hi>owne lips, to receive</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Seven fragrant kiſſes, and the reſt
among,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>One honey-kiſſe, and one touch from her
tongue.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Which being publiſhed, the great defire</l>
                     <l>Of this reward, ſet all mens hearts on fire.</l>
                     <l>So that poore <hi>Pſyche</hi> durſt no more forbeare</l>
                     <l>To offer up her ſelfe: then drawing neare</l>
                     <l>To <hi>Venus</hi> houſe, a Maid of hers, by name</l>
                     <l>Call'd <hi>Cuſtome,</hi> when ſhe ſaw her, did
exclaime,</l>
                     <l>O Madam <hi>Pſyche, Iove</hi> your honour ſave:</l>
                     <l>VVhat doe you feele now, you a Miſtreſſe have?</l>
                     <l>Or does your raſhneſſe, or your ignorant worth</l>
                     <l>Not know, the paines we tooke to find you forth?</l>
                     <l>Sweet, you ſhall for your ſtubborneſſe be
taught:</l>
                     <l>VVith that, rude hold upon her locks ſhe caught,</l>
                     <l>And drag'd her in, and before <hi>Venus</hi> brought.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <pb facs="tcp:12481:36"/>
                  <head>The ſecond Section.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>SO ſoone as <hi>Venus</hi> ſaw her, ſhe like one,</l>
                     <l>That looks 'twixt ſcorne, and indignation,</l>
                     <l>Rais'd a loud laughter, ſuch as does proceed</l>
                     <l>From one, that is vext furiouſly indeed.</l>
                     <l>Then ſhaking of her head, biting hert thumb,</l>
                     <l>She ſayd, what my good daughter are you come</l>
                     <l>Your Mother to ſalute? But I beleeve,</l>
                     <l>You would your husband viſite, who does grieve</l>
                     <l>For the late burne, with which you did inure</l>
                     <l>His tender ſhoulder, but yet reſt ſecure</l>
                     <l>I ſhall provide for you, nor will I ſwerve</l>
                     <l>From any needfull office you deſerve.</l>
                     <l>Thus winking <hi>Venus</hi> did on <hi>Pſyche</hi>
leere,</l>
                     <l>And with ſuch cruell kindneſſe did her jeere.</l>
                     <l>Then for her entertainment, cryes, where are</l>
                     <l>My two rough hand-maids, <hi>Solitude,</hi> and
<hi>Care?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>They enter'd; ſhe commands her hands to tye,</l>
                     <l>And take the poore mayd to their cuſtody.</l>
                     <l>Which done accordingly, with whips they beate,</l>
                     <l>And her with torments miſerably intreate.</l>
                     <l>Thus us'd, and in this ſhamefull manner dight,</l>
                     <l>They her, with ſcorne, reduce to <hi>Venus</hi>
ſight:</l>
                     <l>Who ſmiling ſaid, 'tis more then time, that I</l>
                     <l>Should ſet my Nymphs all to worke ſempſtery,</l>
                     <l>And make your Baby-clouts: why this is brave,</l>
                     <l>And you ſhall <hi>Iuno</hi> for your Mid-wife have.</l>
                     <l>VVhere will you lye in? how farre are you gone?</l>
                     <l>That's a great motive to compaſſion.</l>
                     <l>And I my ſtile muſt rather boaſt, than ſmother,</l>
                     <l>That in my youth ſhall be call'd Grandmother.</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12481:37"/>
                     <l>But by your leave, I doubt theſe Marriages,</l>
                     <l>That are ſolemniz'd without witneſſes:</l>
                     <l>Without conſent of friends, the parties ſtate</l>
                     <l>Vnequall to, are ſcarſe legitimate,</l>
                     <l>And ſo this child, they ſhall a baſtard call:</l>
                     <l>If yet thou bringſt forth any child at all.</l>
                     <l>Then to begin with ſome revenge, ſhe roſe;</l>
                     <l>And all her ornaments did diſcompoſe,</l>
                     <l>And her diſcolour'd Gowne in pieces pull,</l>
                     <l>And what ſoever made her beautifull.</l>
                     <l>But leaſt her ſufferings ſhould all paſſive
be,</l>
                     <l>She turnes her puniſhment to induſtry,</l>
                     <l>And takes of ſeverall Seedes, a certaine meaſure;</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Wheat, Barley, Oates,</hi> and a confuſed
treaſure</l>
                     <l>Of <hi>Peaſe,</hi> and <hi>Lentiles,</hi> then all mixt,
did pour</l>
                     <l>Into one heape, with a prefixed houre,</l>
                     <l>That ere her ſelfe ſhould on our Hemiſpheare,</l>
                     <l>That might, as the bright evening Starre appeare.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Pſyche</hi> each Graine ſhould rightly
ſegregate,</l>
                     <l>A taſque for twenty to elaborate.</l>
                     <l>This worke aſſign'd, <hi>Venus</hi> from thence did
paſſe,</l>
                     <l>To a Marriage Feaſt, where ſhe invited was.</l>
                     <l>Poore <hi>Pſyche</hi> all alone amaz'd did ſtand,</l>
                     <l>Nor to this labour would once ſet her hand:</l>
                     <l>In her owne thoughts judging her ſelfe unable,</l>
                     <l>To vanquiſh that, was ſo inextricable;</l>
                     <l>When loe, a numerous multitude of <hi>Ants,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Her neighbours, the next feilds inhabitants,</l>
                     <l>Came thronging in, ſent thether by ſome power,</l>
                     <l>That pitty tooke on <hi>Cupids Paramour.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Nor would that wrong ſhould be without defence,</l>
                     <l>And hated <hi>Venus</hi> for her inſolence.</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12481:37"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12481:38"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12481:38"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12481:39"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12481:39"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12481:40"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12481:40"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12481:41"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12481:41"/>
                     <l>All theſe by an inſtinct together met,</l>
                     <l>Themſelves in a tumultuous method ſet</l>
                     <l>On worke, and each graine <hi>Arithmetically</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Subſtract, devide, and after multiply.</l>
                     <l>And when that this was done, away they fled:</l>
                     <l>Each graine being by its kind diſtinguiſhed.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Venus</hi> now from the Nuptiall feaſt was come,</l>
                     <l>Her breath perfum'd with wine, and <hi>Balſamum,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Her body was with twines of <hi>Mirtles</hi> bound,</l>
                     <l>Her head with Garlands of ſweet <hi>Roſes</hi>
crown'd.</l>
                     <l>And ſeeing this accompliſht taske, ſhe ſaid</l>
                     <l>Huſwiſe, twas not your handy worke convay'd</l>
                     <l>Theſe ſeedes in order thus; but his, that ſtill</l>
                     <l>Perſiſts in love; to thine, and his owne ill.</l>
                     <l>Then on the ground ſhe threw a cruſt of bread,</l>
                     <l>For <hi>Pſyches</hi> ſupper, and ſo went to bed.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Cupid</hi> the while, in a backe roome was put</l>
                     <l>Vnder the ſame roofe, and in priſon ſhut:</l>
                     <l>A puniſhment forhis old luxury,</l>
                     <l>Leaſt he with <hi>Pſyche</hi> ſhould accompany:</l>
                     <l>And ſo by too much ſtrayning of his ſide,</l>
                     <l>Might hurt his wound, before twas ſcarrify'd:</l>
                     <l>But when the Rofie morning drew away,</l>
                     <l>The ſable curtaine, which let in the day,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Venus</hi> to <hi>Pſyche</hi> calls, and bids
awake,</l>
                     <l>Who ſtanding up, ſhe ſhewes to her a Lake;</l>
                     <l>Environ'd with a rock, beyond whoſe ſteepe</l>
                     <l>And craggy bottome, graz'd a flock of ſheepe:</l>
                     <l>They had no ſhepheard, them to feede, or fold,</l>
                     <l>And yet their well growne fleeces were of gold.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Pallas</hi> ſometimes, the pretious lockes would
cull,</l>
                     <l>To make great <hi>Iuno</hi> veſtures of the wooll:</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12481:42"/>
                     <l>Fetch me, ſayes <hi>Venus,</hi> ſome of that rich
haire,</l>
                     <l>But how you'll doe it, I nor know, nor care.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Pſyche</hi> obayes, not out of hope to win,</l>
                     <l>So great a prize, but meaning to leape in,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hat in
the mariſh ſhe might end her life,</l>
                     <l>Tnd ſo be free'd from <hi>Venus,</hi> and her
ſtrife:</l>
                     <l>When drawing neere, the wind inſpired reed,</l>
                     <l>Spake with a tune full voice. <hi>Pſyche</hi> take
heed,</l>
                     <l>Let not deſpaire, thee of thy ſoule beguile,</l>
                     <l>Nor theſe my waters with thy death defile:</l>
                     <l>But reſt thee heere, under this Willow tree,</l>
                     <l>That growing drinkes of the ſame ſtreame with me;</l>
                     <l>Keepe from thoſe ſheepe, that heated with the ſun,</l>
                     <l>Rage like the <hi>Lyon,</hi> or the <hi>Scorpion;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>None can their ſtony browes, nor hornes abide,</l>
                     <l>Till the dayes fire be ſome what qualifi'd.</l>
                     <l>But when the vapour, and their thirſt is quencht,</l>
                     <l>And <hi>Phebus</hi> horſes in the Ocean drencht,</l>
                     <l>Then you may fetch, what <hi>Venus</hi> does deſire,</l>
                     <l>And find their fleecy gold on every bryer:</l>
                     <l>Th'oraculous Reed full of humanity,</l>
                     <l>Thus from her hollow wombe did Propheſie</l>
                     <l>And ſhe obſerving ſtrictly what was taught,</l>
                     <l>Her apron full of the ſoft mettle brought,</l>
                     <l>And gave to <hi>Venus;</hi> yet her gift, and labour,</l>
                     <l>Gayn'd no acceptance, nor found any favour.</l>
                     <l>I know the author of this fact, ſayes ſhe,</l>
                     <l>How' twas the price of his adultery.</l>
                     <l>But now I will a ſerious tryall make,</l>
                     <l>Whether you doe theſe dangers undertake</l>
                     <l>With courage, and that wiſedome you pretend.</l>
                     <l>For ſee that lofty Mountaine, whence deſcend</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12481:42"/>
                     <l>Black-colour'd waters, from earths horrid dennes,</l>
                     <l>And with their boylings waſh the <hi>Stygian</hi>
fennes.</l>
                     <l>From thence augment <hi>Cocytus</hi> foaming rage,</l>
                     <l>And ſwell his channell with their ſurpluſſage.</l>
                     <l>Goe now, and ſome of that dead liquor skim,</l>
                     <l>And fill this Chriſtall Pitcher to the brim:</l>
                     <l>Bring it me ſtraight, and ſo her browes did knit,</l>
                     <l>Threatning great matters, if ſhe fail'd of it.</l>
                     <l>With this injunction <hi>Pſyche</hi> went her wayes,</l>
                     <l>Hoping even there to end her wretched dayes.</l>
                     <l>But comming neere to the prefixed place,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe height did couit the clouds, &amp; loweſt
baſe,</l>
                     <l>Gave thoſe black ſtreames their firſt originall,</l>
                     <l>That wearing the hard rocks, did headlong fall</l>
                     <l>Into the <hi>Stygian</hi> vallies, underneath</l>
                     <l>She ſaw a fatall thing, and full of death.</l>
                     <l>Two watchfull Dragons the ſtraight paſſage kept,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe eyes were never ſeal'd, nor ever ſlept.</l>
                     <l>The waters too ſaid ſomething, <hi>Pſyche,</hi>
flye;</l>
                     <l>What doe you here? depart, or you ſhall dye.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Pſyche</hi> with terrour of the voyce dejected,</l>
                     <l>And thought of that might never be effected,</l>
                     <l>Like <hi>Niobe,</hi> was chang'd into a ſtone,</l>
                     <l>In body preſent, but her minde was gone.</l>
                     <l>And in the midſt of her great griefe, and feares,</l>
                     <l>Could not enjoy the comfort of her teares.</l>
                     <l>When <hi>Iove,</hi> whoſe ſtill protecting
providence</l>
                     <l>Is ever ready to helpe innocence:</l>
                     <l>Sent the <hi>Saturnian</hi> Eagle, who once led</l>
                     <l>By <hi>Loves</hi> impulſion, ſnatcht up
<hi>Ganimed</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>To be <hi>Ioves</hi> Cup-bearer, from <hi>Ida</hi> hill,</l>
                     <l>Andever ſince bore <hi>Cupid</hi> a good-will:</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12481:43"/>
                     <l>And what he could not to his perſon ſhow,</l>
                     <l>Reſolv'd upon his Miſtreſſe to beſtow.</l>
                     <l>Then with Angelick ſpeed, when he had left</l>
                     <l>The Ayres high tracts, and the three Regions cleft,</l>
                     <l>Before her face he on the meadow ſate,</l>
                     <l>And ſaid, alaſſe, thou inconſiderate,</l>
                     <l>And fooliſh Maid, returne back, goe not nigh</l>
                     <l>Thoſe ſacred ſtreames, ſo full or majeſty.</l>
                     <l>What hope haſt thou thoſe waters to procure,</l>
                     <l>VVhich <hi>Iove</hi> himſelfe does tremble to abjure?</l>
                     <l>No mortall hand may be allowd to touch,</l>
                     <l>Much leſſe to ſteale a drop, their power is
ſuch.</l>
                     <l>Give me the Pitcher, ſhe it gave; he went</l>
                     <l>To <hi>Styx,</hi> and fain'd that <hi>Venus</hi> had him
ſent.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Pſyche</hi> the Vrne did to his tallons tye,</l>
                     <l>Then with his plumed oares poiz'd equally,</l>
                     <l>He lets it ſinke bet wixt the very jawes</l>
                     <l>Of thoſe fierce Dragons, and then up it drawes,</l>
                     <l>And gives it <hi>Pſyche;</hi> ſhe the ſame
convay'd</l>
                     <l>To <hi>Venus,</hi> yet her paines were ill apayd.</l>
                     <l>Nothing her rage might expiate, but ſtill</l>
                     <l>The end of one, begins another ill.</l>
                     <l>For ought, ſayes <hi>Venus,</hi> that I gather can,</l>
                     <l>You are a VVitch, or ſome Magitian.</l>
                     <l>What elſe can be concluded put of theſe</l>
                     <l>Experienc'd impoſſibilities?</l>
                     <l>If your commerce be ſuch then, you may venter</l>
                     <l>Boldly to Hell, and when you there ſhall enter,</l>
                     <l>Me to my couſen <hi>Proſerpine</hi> commend,</l>
                     <l>And in my name intreat her, ſhe would ſend</l>
                     <l>Some of her Boxe of beauty to me; ſay,</l>
                     <l>So much as may ſuffice me for a day:</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12481:43"/>
                     <l>Excuſe me to her, that my owne is ſpent,</l>
                     <l>I know not how, by an ill accident.</l>
                     <l>I am aſham'd to ſpeake it, but 'tis gone,</l>
                     <l>And waſted all in curing of my ſonne.</l>
                     <l>But be not ſlack in your returne; for I</l>
                     <l>Muſt with the <hi>gods</hi> feaſt of neceſſity.</l>
                     <l>Nor can I thither goe, without diſgrace,</l>
                     <l>Till I have us'd ſome art unto my face.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Pfyche</hi> conceiv'd now, that her life, and fate,</l>
                     <l>And fortunes all were at their utmoſt date,</l>
                     <l>Being by <hi>Venus</hi> cruelty thruſt on,</l>
                     <l>Towards a manifeſt deſtruction:</l>
                     <l>Which ſhe collects by argument, that thus</l>
                     <l>With her owne feete, muſt march to <hi>Tanarus.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>In this deluſive agony ſhe roſe,</l>
                     <l>And by degrees, up to a Turret goes,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe top orelook't the hills, it was ſo high,</l>
                     <l>Reſolv'd to tumble headlong from the skie:</l>
                     <l>Conceiting as her fancy did her feed,</l>
                     <l>That was the way to goe to Hell indeed.</l>
                     <l>But then a ſuddaine voice to her did call,</l>
                     <l>Which brake out of the cavernes of the wall,</l>
                     <l>That ſaid, ah coward wretch, why doſt thou yeeld</l>
                     <l>To this laſt labour, and forſake the field?</l>
                     <l>Whilſt <hi>Victory</hi> her Banner does diſplay,</l>
                     <l>And with a profer'd Crowne, tempts thee to ſtay.</l>
                     <l>The way to Hell is eaſie, and the gate</l>
                     <l>Stands ope; but if the ſoule be ſeparate</l>
                     <l>Thus from the body, true, ſhe goes to Hell:</l>
                     <l>Not to returne, but there for ever dwell.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Vertue</hi> knows no ſuch ſtop, nor they, whom
<hi>Iove</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Either begot, or equally does love.</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12481:44"/>
                     <l>Now liſt to me; there is a fatall ground</l>
                     <l>In <hi>Greece,</hi> beyond <hi>Achaia's</hi> fartheſt
bound,</l>
                     <l>Neare <hi>Lacedemon,</hi> famous for the rape</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Paris</hi> on <hi>Hellen</hi> made, and their
eſcape.</l>
                     <l>Tis quickly found; for with its ſteemy breath</l>
                     <l>It blaſts the fields, and is the portof death.</l>
                     <l>The path, like <hi>Ariadnes</hi> clue does guide</l>
                     <l>To the darke Court, where <hi>Pluto</hi> does abide:</l>
                     <l>And if you muſt thoſe diſmall regions ſee,</l>
                     <l>Then carry in your hand a double fee.</l>
                     <l>For <hi>Charon</hi> will doe nothing without money;</l>
                     <l>And you muſt have ſops made of meale, and honey.</l>
                     <l>It is a doubtfull paſſage, for there are</l>
                     <l>Many Decrees, and Lawes peculiar</l>
                     <l>Muſt ſtrictly be obſerv'd; and if once broke,</l>
                     <l>No ranſome, nor entreaty can revoke.</l>
                     <l>Nor is there proſecution of more ſtrife,</l>
                     <l>But all are penall ſtatutes on your life.</l>
                     <l>The firſt that you ſhall meete with, as you
paſſe,</l>
                     <l>Is an old man come driving of an aſſe,</l>
                     <l>Decrepid as himſelfe, they both ſhall ſweat</l>
                     <l>VVith their hard labour, and fee ſhall intreat,</l>
                     <l>That you would helpe his burthen to unty;</l>
                     <l>But give no eare, nor ſtay when you goe by.</l>
                     <l>And next you ſhall arrive without delay</l>
                     <l>To ſlow <hi>Avernus</hi> Lake, where you muſt pay</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Charon</hi> his waftage, as before I ſaid,</l>
                     <l>For avarice does live among the dead:</l>
                     <l>And a poore man, though tyde ſerve, and the wind,</l>
                     <l>If he no ſtipend bring, muſt ſtay behind.</l>
                     <l>Here as you ſayle along, you ſhall ſee one</l>
                     <l>Of ſqualid hue, they call <hi>Oblivion,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12481:44"/>
                     <l>Heave up his hands, and on the waters floate,</l>
                     <l>Praying, you would receive him in your Boate:</l>
                     <l>But know, all thoſe that will in ſafety be,</l>
                     <l>Muſt learne to diſaffect ſuch piety.</l>
                     <l>When you are landed, and a little paſt</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Stygian</hi> Ferry, you your eyes ſhall
caſt,</l>
                     <l>And ſpy ſome buſie at their wheele, and theſe</l>
                     <l>Are three old women, call'd the Deſtinies;</l>
                     <l>They will deſire you, to ſit downe, and ſpin,</l>
                     <l>And ſhew your owne lifes thread upon the pin.</l>
                     <l>Yet are they all but ſnares, and doe proceed</l>
                     <l>From <hi>Venus</hi> malice, to corrupt your creed.</l>
                     <l>For ſhould you lend your helpe to ſpin, or card,</l>
                     <l>Or meddle with their diſtaffe, your reward</l>
                     <l>Might perhaps ſlip out of your hand, and then</l>
                     <l>You muſt hope never to come back againe.</l>
                     <l>Next, a huge Maſtiffe ſhall you ſee, before</l>
                     <l>The Palace-gate, and <hi>Adamantine</hi> dore</l>
                     <l>That leads to <hi>Dis,</hi> who when he opens wide</l>
                     <l>His triple throate, the ghoſts are terrifi'd</l>
                     <l>With his loud barkins, which ſo farre rebound,</l>
                     <l>They make all Hell to Eccho with their ſound:</l>
                     <l>Him with a morſell you muſt firſt aſſwage,</l>
                     <l>And then deliver <hi>Venus</hi> Embaſſage.</l>
                     <l>For <hi>Proſerpine</hi> ſhall kindly you intreat,</l>
                     <l>And will provide a banquet, and a ſeat.</l>
                     <l>But if you ſit, fit on the ground, and taſte</l>
                     <l>None of her dainties, but declare in haſte</l>
                     <l>VVhat you deſire, which ſhe will ſtraight deliver:</l>
                     <l>Then with thoſe former rules, paſſe backe the
river.</l>
                     <l>Give the three-headed dogge his other ſhare,</l>
                     <l>And to the greedy Marriner his fare.</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12481:45"/>
                     <l>Keepe faſt theſe precepts what ſoere they be,</l>
                     <l>And thinke on <hi>Orpheus,</hi> and <hi>Euridice.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>But above all things, this obſerve to doe,</l>
                     <l>Take heed, you open not, nor pry into</l>
                     <l>The beauties Boxe, elſe ſhall you there remaine;</l>
                     <l>Nor ſee this Heaven, nor theſe Starres againe.</l>
                     <l>The ſtone incloſed voyce, did friendly thus</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Pſyche</hi> forewarne, with ſignes propitious.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>The laſt Section.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>SO ſoone as <hi>Pſyche</hi> got all things together,</l>
                     <l>That might be uſefull for her going thither,</l>
                     <l>And her returne, to <hi>Tanarus</hi> ſhe went,</l>
                     <l>And the Infernall paſſage did attempt:</l>
                     <l>VVhere all thoſe ſtrange, and fatall propheſies</l>
                     <l>Accompliſht were in their occurrences.</l>
                     <l>For firſt ſhe paſſes by with careleſſe
ſpeed,</l>
                     <l>The old man, and his Aſſe, and gave no heed</l>
                     <l>Either unto his perſon, or deſire.</l>
                     <l>And next ſhe payes the Ferry-man his hire;</l>
                     <l>And though <hi>Oblivion,</hi> and the Fates did woe her,</l>
                     <l>VVith many ſtrong temptations, to undoe her,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Vliſſes</hi> like, ſhe did their prayers
decline,</l>
                     <l>And came now to the houſe of <hi>Proſerpine.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Before the Palace was a ſtately Court,</l>
                     <l>Where forty Marble-pillars did ſupport</l>
                     <l>The roofe, and frontiſ-piece, that bore on high</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Pluto's</hi> owne ſtatue, grav'd in Ebony.</l>
                     <l>His face, though full of majeſty, was dim'd</l>
                     <l>With a ſad cloud, and his rude throne untrim'd:</l>
                     <l>His golden Scepter was eate in with ruſt,</l>
                     <l>And that againe quite overlays with duſt.</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12481:45"/>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Ceres</hi> was wrought him by, with weeping eyne,</l>
                     <l>Lamenting for the loſſe of <hi>Preſerpine.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Her daughters rape was there ſet downe at full,</l>
                     <l>Who while that ſhe too ſtudiouſly did pull</l>
                     <l>The purple Violet, and ſanguine Roſe,</l>
                     <l>Lillies, and low growne Panſies; to compoſe</l>
                     <l>Wreathes for the Nymphes, regardles of her health</l>
                     <l>'Twas ſoone ſurpriz'd, and ſnacht away by
ſtealth.</l>
                     <l>Forc'd by the King of the infernall powers,</l>
                     <l>And ſeem'd to cry, and looke after her flowers.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Enceladus</hi> was ſtrecht upon his backe,</l>
                     <l>While <hi>Plutoes</hi> Horſe hoofes, and coach did
wracke</l>
                     <l>His bruiſed body. <hi>Pallas</hi> did extend</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Gorgons</hi> head. <hi>Delia</hi> her bow did
bend;</l>
                     <l>And Virgins both, their Vncle did defy</l>
                     <l>Like Champions, to defend virginity.</l>
                     <l>The Sun, and Stars were wrapt in ſable weedes,</l>
                     <l>Dampt with the breath, of his <hi>Tanarian</hi> Steedes.</l>
                     <l>All theſe, and more were portray'd round about,</l>
                     <l>VVhich filth defac'd, or time had eaten out.</l>
                     <l>Three headed <hi>Cerberus</hi> the gate did keepe,</l>
                     <l>VVhom <hi>Pſyche</hi> with a ſop firſt layd to
ſleepe;</l>
                     <l>And then went ſafely by, where firſt ſhe ſaw</l>
                     <l>Hells Iudges ſit, and urging of the law:</l>
                     <l>The place was parted in two ſeverall wayes,</l>
                     <l>The right hand to <hi>Elyſium</hi> convayes;</l>
                     <l>But on the left, were male factors ſent,</l>
                     <l>The ſeate of tortures, and ſtrange puniſhment.</l>
                     <l>There <hi>Tantalus</hi> ſtands thirſty to the chin,</l>
                     <l>In water, but can take no liquor in.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Ixion</hi> too, and <hi>Sifiphus;</hi> the one</l>
                     <l>A wheele, the other turnes a reſtleſſe ſtone.</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12481:46"/>
                     <l>A Vulture there on <hi>Titius</hi> does wreake</l>
                     <l>The Gods juſt wrath, and pounding with his beake,</l>
                     <l>On his immortall liver ſtill does feed,</l>
                     <l>For what the day does waſt, the night does breed:</l>
                     <l>And other ſoules are forced to reveale,</l>
                     <l>VVhat unjuſt pleaſures they on Earth did ſteale;</l>
                     <l>Whom fiery <hi>Phlegeton</hi> does round incloſe,</l>
                     <l>And <hi>Stix</hi> his waves does nine times interpoſe.</l>
                     <l>The noyſe of whipps, and Furies, did ſo fright</l>
                     <l>Poore <hi>Pſyches</hi> eares, ſhe haſted to the
right.</l>
                     <l>That path way ſtraight, for on each ſide there grew</l>
                     <l>A Grove of moumefull <hi>Cypreſſe,</hi> and of
<hi>Yew:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>It is the place of ſuch as happy dye.</l>
                     <l>There, as ſhe walked on, did Infants cry,</l>
                     <l>Whom cruell death ſnacht from their teats away,</l>
                     <l>And rob'd of ſweet life, in an evill day.</l>
                     <l>There Lovers live, who living here, were wiſe;</l>
                     <l>And had their Ladies, to cloſe up their eyes.</l>
                     <l>There Mighty <hi>Heroes</hi> walke, that ſpent their
bloud,</l>
                     <l>In a juſt cauſe, and for their Countries good.</l>
                     <l>All theſe beholding through the glimering ayre,</l>
                     <l>A mortall; and ſo exquiſitely faire,</l>
                     <l>Thicke as the motes, in the Sun beames came ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</l>
                     <l>To gaze, and know the cauſe too of her comming;</l>
                     <l>Which ſhe diſſembled; onely askt to know,</l>
                     <l>Where <hi>Pluto</hi> dwelt, for thither ſhe muſt
goe:</l>
                     <l>A guide was ſtraight aſſign'd, who did attend,</l>
                     <l>And <hi>Pſyche</hi> brought ſafe to her journies
end,</l>
                     <l>Who being entred, proſtrate on her knee,</l>
                     <l>She humbly tenders <hi>Venus</hi> Embaſſy.</l>
                     <l>Great <hi>Plutoes</hi> Queene preſented to her
gueſt,</l>
                     <l>A Princely <hi>Throne</hi> to fit on, and a feaſt,</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12481:46"/>
                     <l>Wiſhing her taſt, and her tyr'd limbes refreſſe,</l>
                     <l>After her journey, and her wearineſſe.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Pſyche</hi> excus'd it, that ſhe could not
ſtay,</l>
                     <l>And if ſhe had her arrant would away.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>But <hi>Proſerpine</hi> reply'd, you doe not know</l>
                     <l>Faire Mayd, the joyes and pleaſures are below,</l>
                     <l>Stay and poſſeſſe, what ever I call mine,</l>
                     <l>For other Lights, and other Starres doe ſhine</l>
                     <l>VVithin our territories, the day's not loſt,</l>
                     <l>As you imagine, in <hi>Elyſian</hi> coaſt.</l>
                     <l>The Golden <hi>Age,</hi> and Progeny is heere,</l>
                     <l>And that Fam'd <hi>Tree,</hi> that does in <hi>Autumne</hi>
beare</l>
                     <l>Cluſters of Gold, whoſe <hi>Apples</hi> thou ſhalt
hoard,</l>
                     <l>Or each meale, if thou pleaſe, ſet on the board.</l>
                     <l>The Matrons of <hi>Elyſium</hi> at thy becke,</l>
                     <l>Shall come and goe; and buried Queenes ſhall deck</l>
                     <l>Thy body, in more ſtately ornaments,</l>
                     <l>Then all Earths fayned Majeſty preſents:</l>
                     <l>The pale and ſqualid region ſhall rejoyce,</l>
                     <l>Silence ſhall breake forth a pleaſant voice:</l>
                     <l>Sterne <hi>Pluto</hi> ſhall himſelfe to mirth
betake,</l>
                     <l>And crowned Ghoſts ſhall banquet for thy ſake;</l>
                     <l>New Lampes ſhall burne, if thou wilt here abide,</l>
                     <l>And nights thicke darkeneſſe ſhall be rarifi'd,</l>
                     <l>What ere the winds upon the Earth doe ſweepe</l>
                     <l>Rivers, or Fennes embrace, or the vaſt deepe,</l>
                     <l>Shall be thy tribute; and I will deliver</l>
                     <l>Vp for thy Servant, the <hi>Lethean</hi> River:</l>
                     <l>Beſides the <hi>Parca</hi> ſhall thy Hand-maides be,</l>
                     <l>And what thou ſpeak'ſt, ſtand for a deſtiny.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Pſyche</hi> gave thankes; but did her plainely
tell,</l>
                     <l>She would not be a Courtier unto hell:</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12481:47"/>
                     <l>When wondring that ſuch honours did not pleaſe,</l>
                     <l>She offerd gifts, farre richer, then all theſe.</l>
                     <l>For as a Dowry, at her feet ſhe laid</l>
                     <l>The mighty engines, which the world upwaigh'd,</l>
                     <l>And vow'd to give her immortality,</l>
                     <l>And all the pleaſures, and the royalty</l>
                     <l>Of the <hi>Elyſian</hi> Fields; which wiſely ſhe</l>
                     <l>Refus'd, for Hell, with all their power, and skill,</l>
                     <l>Though they allure, they cannot force the will:</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>This vext faire <hi>Proſerpine,</hi> any ſhould know</l>
                     <l>Their horrid ſecrets, and have power to ſhow,</l>
                     <l>Vnto the upper world, what ſhe had ſeene</l>
                     <l>Of Hell, and <hi>Styx,</hi> of <hi>Pluto,</hi> and his
Queene,</l>
                     <l>Yet ſince ſhe might not her owne lawes withſtand,</l>
                     <l>She gave the boxe of beauty in her hand.</l>
                     <l>And <hi>Pſyche,</hi> with thoſe precepts us'd
before,</l>
                     <l>The Sunnes bright beames did once againe adore</l>
                     <l>Then, as ſhe thought, being out of all controule,</l>
                     <l>A curious raſhneſſe did poſſeſſe her
ſoule,</l>
                     <l>That ſlighting of her charge, and pormis'd duty,</l>
                     <l>She greatly itcht, to adde to her owne beauty;</l>
                     <l>Saying, ah foole, to bear ſo rich a prize,</l>
                     <l>And yet through feare, doſt envy thine owne eyes</l>
                     <l>The happy object, whoſe reflexion might,</l>
                     <l>Gaine thee ſome favour, in young <hi>Cupids</hi>
ſight:</l>
                     <l>The voyce forbad me, but I now am free,</l>
                     <l>From <hi>Venus</hi> viſion, and Hells cuſtody.</l>
                     <l>And ſo without all ſcruple, ſhe unlocks,</l>
                     <l>And lets forth the whole treaſure of the boxe,</l>
                     <l>VVhich was not any thing to make one faire,</l>
                     <l>But a meere <hi>Stygian,</hi> and infernall ayre;</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12481:47"/>
                     <l>Whoſe ſubtle breathings through her pores did
creepe,</l>
                     <l>And ſtuft her body with a cloud of ſleepe,</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>But <hi>Cupid</hi> now, not able to endure</l>
                     <l>Her longer abſence, having gain'd his cure,</l>
                     <l>And prun'd his ruffled wings, flew through the gate</l>
                     <l>Of his cloſe priſon, to ſeeke out his Mate:</l>
                     <l>Where finding her in this dull Lethargy,</l>
                     <l>He drew the foggy vapour from her eye;</l>
                     <l>And that her ſtupid ſpirits might awake,</l>
                     <l>Did all the drow ſie exhalation ſhake</l>
                     <l>From off her ſence; ſhe ſhut it up, and ſeal'd</l>
                     <l>The Boxe ſo faſt, it ne're might be reveal'd.</l>
                     <l>Next, with his harmeleſſe Dart, ſmall as a pin,</l>
                     <l>He prick't the <hi>ſuperficies</hi> of her skin:</l>
                     <l>Saying, what wondrous frailty does poſſeſſe</l>
                     <l>This female kind, or rather wilfulneſſe?</l>
                     <l>For loe, thy fooliſh curioſity,</l>
                     <l>Has tempted thee againe to perjury.</l>
                     <l>VVhat proud exploit was this? what horrid fact?</l>
                     <l>Be ſure, my mother <hi>Venus</hi> will exact</l>
                     <l>A ſtrict accompt, of all that has beene done,</l>
                     <l>Both of thy ſelfe, and thy commiſſion.</l>
                     <l>But yet for all this treſpaſſe, be of cheere,</l>
                     <l>And in a humble duty perſevere,</l>
                     <l>Detaine from <hi>Venus</hi> nought, that is her owne,</l>
                     <l>And for what elſe remaines, let me alone.</l>
                     <l>Thus <hi>Pſyche</hi> by her Lover being ſent,</l>
                     <l>And waxing ſtrong, through his encouragement,</l>
                     <l>The Boxe of beauty unto <hi>Venus</hi> brings,</l>
                     <l>Whilſt <hi>Cupid</hi> did betake him wings:</l>
                     <l>For when he ſaw his Mother ſo auſtere,</l>
                     <l>Forc'd by the violence of love, and feare,</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12481:48"/>
                     <l>He pierced the Marble concave of the sky,</l>
                     <l>To Heaven appeal'd, and did for Juſtice cry;</l>
                     <l>Pleading his cauſe, and in the ſacred preſence</l>
                     <l>Of <hi>Iove</hi> himſelfe, did his Love-ſuit
commence.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Iove</hi> at his ſight, threw by his rayes, ſo
pure,</l>
                     <l>That no eyes but his owne might them endure:</l>
                     <l>Whom <hi>Cupid</hi> thus beſpake: Great <hi>Iove,</hi> if
I</l>
                     <l>Am borne your true, and lawfull progeny:</l>
                     <l>If I have playd bet weene your armes, and ſate</l>
                     <l>Next to your ſelfe, but ſince growne to a ſtate</l>
                     <l>Of riper yeeres, have beene thought fit to beare</l>
                     <l>An equall ſway, and move in the ſame ſpeare</l>
                     <l>Of honour with you, by whoſe meanes, both men,</l>
                     <l>And <hi>gods</hi> have trembled at my Bow, as when</l>
                     <l>Your ſelfe have darted thunder-bolts, and ſlaine</l>
                     <l>The earth bred Gyants, in the <hi>Phlegrian</hi> Plaine.</l>
                     <l>And when in ſeverall ſcales my ſhafts were layd</l>
                     <l>With your owne <hi>Trident,</hi> neither has
out-waigh'd.</l>
                     <l>I come not now, that you ſhould either give,</l>
                     <l>Confirme, or adde to my prerogative.</l>
                     <l>But ſetting all command, and power aſide,</l>
                     <l>Deſire by law, and juſtice to be try'd.</l>
                     <l>For whither elſe ſhould I appeale? or bring</l>
                     <l>My cauſe, but to your ſelfe, that are a King,</l>
                     <l>And father to us all, and can diſpence</l>
                     <l>What right you pleaſe, in Court, and Conſcience?</l>
                     <l>I have beene wrong'd, and muſt, with griefe indite</l>
                     <l>My Mother of much cruelty, and ſpight</l>
                     <l>To me, and my poore <hi>Pſyche:</hi> there's but one,</l>
                     <l>In the whole world, that my affection,</l>
                     <l>And fancy likes, where others doe eujoy</l>
                     <l>So many; the diverſity does cloy</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12481:48"/>
                     <l>Their very appetite: yet who but owes</l>
                     <l>All his delight to me? and <hi>Venus</hi> knows,</l>
                     <l>By her owne thoughts, the uncontrouled fire</l>
                     <l>That reignes in youth, when <hi>love</hi> does him
inſpire.</l>
                     <l>Yet ſhe without all pitty, or remorſe,</l>
                     <l>Me, and my Miſtreſſe, labours to divorce.</l>
                     <l>I covet no ones ſpouſe, nor have I taken</l>
                     <l>Anothers Love; there's not a man forſaken,</l>
                     <l>Or <hi>god,</hi> for my ſake, that bewayles his deare,</l>
                     <l>Or bathes his ſpoyled boſome with a teare:</l>
                     <l>Then why ſhould any, me, and my Love ſever?</l>
                     <l>That joyne all other hearts, and loves together?</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Iove</hi> heard him out, and did applaud his
ſpeach,</l>
                     <l>And both his hand, and Scepter to him reach.</l>
                     <l>Then calling <hi>Cupid,</hi> his ſmooth fingers layd</l>
                     <l>On his <hi>Ambroſiack</hi> cheeke, and kiſſing
ſayd,</l>
                     <l>My little youngſter, and my ſonne, 'tis true;</l>
                     <l>That I have never yet receiv'd from you</l>
                     <l>Any due reverence, or reſpective meed,</l>
                     <l>Which all the other <hi>gods</hi> to me decreed.</l>
                     <l>For this my heart, whoſe high preheminence</l>
                     <l>Gives Edicts to the Starres, and does diſpence</l>
                     <l>The like to Nature, your fine hand the while,</l>
                     <l>With earthly luſts ſtill labours to defile;</l>
                     <l>And contrary to publick diſcipline,</l>
                     <l>And 'gainſt all lawes, both Morall, and Divine,</l>
                     <l>Chiefly the <hi>Iulian,</hi> thou doſt fill mine eyes</l>
                     <l>With many foule, and cloſe adulteries.</l>
                     <l>For how ofttimes, have I through vaine deſire</l>
                     <l>Beene chang'd to beaſts, birds, ſerpents, and to
fire?</l>
                     <l>Which has procur'd ill cenſures, and much blame,</l>
                     <l>And hurt my eſtimation, and my fame:</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12481:49"/>
                     <l>Yet being pleas'd with this thy fooliſh ſport,</l>
                     <l>I'me loath to leave it, though I'me ſorry for't;</l>
                     <l>And on condition thou wilt uſe thy wit,</l>
                     <l>In my behalfe, and minde the benefit,</l>
                     <l>I will performe all thy demands: if when</l>
                     <l>Thou ſeeſt faire Damfells on the earth agen,</l>
                     <l>Remembring thou waſt brought up on my knee,</l>
                     <l>That every ſuch Mayd thou wilt bring to mee.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Cupid</hi> aſſents; then <hi>Iove</hi> bids
<hi>Maya's</hi> ſonne,</l>
                     <l>Publiſh a royall Proclamation,</l>
                     <l>Through the Precincts of Heaven, and call at once</l>
                     <l>A generall councell, and a Seſſions,</l>
                     <l>That the whole bench, and race of Deities,</l>
                     <l>Should in their ſeverall rankes, and pedegrees,</l>
                     <l>Repaire ſtraight to his Court, this to be done,</l>
                     <l>In paine of <hi>Ioves</hi> diſpleaſure, and a
ſumme</l>
                     <l>Of money to be laid upon his head,</l>
                     <l>And from his lands, and goods belevied,</l>
                     <l>If any <hi>god</hi> ſhould dare himſelfe abſent,</l>
                     <l>For any cauſe, from this great Parliament:</l>
                     <l>And that whoever had his name i'th' booke,</l>
                     <l>His fyne, but his excuſe ſhould not be tooke.</l>
                     <l>This being nois'd abroad, from every where,</l>
                     <l>The leſſer <hi>gods</hi> came thronging out of
feare,</l>
                     <l>And the Celeſtiall Theater did thwack,</l>
                     <l>That <hi>Atlas</hi> ſeem'd to groane under his pack.</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Iove</hi> out of his Ivory throne did riſe,</l>
                     <l>And thus beſpake them: Conſcript Deities,</l>
                     <l>For ſo the <hi>Muſes</hi> with their whiteſt
ſtone,</l>
                     <l>Have writ your Names, and Titles, every one.</l>
                     <l>You know my Nephew <hi>Cupid;</hi> for the moſt</l>
                     <l>Of us, I'me ſure, have felt him to our coſt:</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12481:49"/>
                     <l>Whoſe youthfull heat I have ſtill ſought in vaine,</l>
                     <l>And his licentious ryot to reſtraine.</l>
                     <l>But that his lewd life be no farther ſpread,</l>
                     <l>His luſts, nor his corruptions publiſhed.</l>
                     <l>I hold it fit, that we the cauſe remove,</l>
                     <l>And bind him in the fetters of chaſt love:</l>
                     <l>And ſince that he has made ſo good a choice,</l>
                     <l>Of his owne wife, let each <hi>god</hi> give his voice,</l>
                     <l>That he enjoy her, and for ever tye</l>
                     <l>Vnto himſelfe, in bands of Matrimony.</l>
                     <l>Then unto <hi>Venus</hi> turning his bright face,</l>
                     <l>Daughter, he ſayes, conceive it no diſgrace,</l>
                     <l>That <hi>Pſyche</hi> marries with your ſonne; for I,</l>
                     <l>That where I pleaſe, give immortality,</l>
                     <l>Will alter her condition, and her ſtate,</l>
                     <l>And make all equall, and legitimate.</l>
                     <l>With that, command to <hi>Mercury</hi> was given,</l>
                     <l>That he ſhould fetch faire <hi>Pſyche</hi> unto
Heaven:</l>
                     <l>And when that ſhe into their preſence came,</l>
                     <l>Her wondrous beauty did each <hi>god</hi> inflame.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Then <hi>Jove</hi> reacht forth a cup with <hi>Nectar</hi>
fraught,</l>
                     <l>And bad her be immortall with the draught:</l>
                     <l>So joyn'd them hand in hand, and vow'd beſide,</l>
                     <l>That ſhe with her deare <hi>Cupid</hi> ſhould abide;</l>
                     <l>Ne're to be ſeparate; and more t'enlarge</l>
                     <l>His bounty, made a Feaſt at his owne charge,</l>
                     <l>Where he plac'd <hi>Cupid</hi> at the upper end,</l>
                     <l>And amorous <hi>Pſyche</hi> on his boſome lean'd.</l>
                     <l>Next ſate himſelfe, and <hi>Iuno,</hi> then each
gueſt,</l>
                     <l>And this great Dinner was by <hi>Vulcan</hi> dreſt.</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Graces</hi> ſtrewd the roome, and made it
ſmile</l>
                     <l>With bluſhing Roſes, and ſweet flowers; the while</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12481:50"/>
                     <l>The ſpheares danc'd harmony. <hi>Apollo</hi> ran</l>
                     <l>Diviſion on his Harpe, <hi>Satyr,</hi> and
<hi>Pan</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Play'd on their Pipes: the Quire of Muſes ſang,</l>
                     <l>And the vaſt concave of <hi>Olimpus</hi> rang,</l>
                     <l>VVith pious acclamations to the Bride;</l>
                     <l>An joy'd that <hi>Pſyche</hi> was thus deify'd.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Hermes,</hi> and <hi>Venus</hi> mov'd their gracefull
Feet,</l>
                     <l>And did in artificiall meaſures ſures meet;</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Phrygian</hi> boy fill'd wine at this great
feaſt,</l>
                     <l>Only to <hi>Iove,</hi> and <hi>Bacchus</hi> to the
reſt.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Thus <hi>Cupid</hi> had his love, and not long after,</l>
                     <l>Her wombe by <hi>Iuno's</hi> helpe, brought forth a
daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</l>
                     <l>A child, by nature different from all,</l>
                     <l>That laught when ſhe was borne, and men did call</l>
                     <l>Her <hi>Pleaſure;</hi> one, that does exhilarate</l>
                     <l>Both Gods, and men, and does her ſelfe dilate</l>
                     <l>Through all ſocieties, chiefly the beſt,</l>
                     <l>VVhere there is any tryumph, or a feaſt.</l>
                     <l>Shee was the <hi>Authour,</hi> that did firſt invent</l>
                     <l>All kinds of ſport, conceits, and meriment:</l>
                     <l>And ſince to all mens humours does incline,</l>
                     <l>Whether, that they be ſenſuall, or Divine.</l>
                     <l>Is of a modeſt, and a looſe behaviour,</l>
                     <l>And of a ſetled, and a wanton favour:</l>
                     <l>Moſt dangerous, when ſhe appeares moſt kind,</l>
                     <l>For then ſhee'll part, and leave a ſting behind:</l>
                     <l>But happy they, that can her ſtill detaine,</l>
                     <l>For where ſhe is moſt fixt, ſhe is leaſt vaine.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12481:50"/>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
